<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Readings on unwiredcouch.com</title>
    <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Readings on unwiredcouch.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the Command–Adapt Paradox: Guided Adaptability to Cope with Complexity</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/paper-command-adapt-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/paper-command-adapt-paradox/</guid>
      <description>Key takeaways The paper discusses the apparent paradox of “plan and conform” (aka centralised control) and “plan and revise” (aka guided adaptability) perspectives in safety management.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways</h2>
<p>The paper discusses the apparent paradox of “plan and conform” (aka centralised control) and “plan and revise” (aka guided adaptability) perspectives in safety management. As the paper discusses, this paradox is only apparent as both are needed in conjunction to navigate an ever faster changing world full of brittleness.</p>
<h2 id="detailed-discussion">Detailed discussion</h2>
<p>The paper starts of with an introduction to failure as a result of brittle systems:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Failure is due to brittle systems, not erratic components, subsystems, or human beings.” (Woods, 2023, p. 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which sets the theme for failure (and success for that matter) being an emergent property of a system that can’t be explained by looking at the individual components alone. This is a very common view on failure in complex systems (see e.g. “Engineering a safer world”) and very important as well later on when discussing the limits of the “plan and conform” perspective.</p>
<p>Brittleness as a core emergent property of systems is subsequently defined as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Descriptively, brittleness is how rapidly a system’s performance declines when it nears and reaches its boundary.” (Woods, 2023, p. 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following from the definition of brittleness the central challenge of operating highly complex systems with emergent behaviour is then stated as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Because competence envelopes are bounded, a core question for all systems is—how does the system perform when events push it near or beyond the edge of its envelope?” (Woods, 2023, p. 3)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And this is very interesting I think because it’s not just the core question for all systems from an engineering and design standpoint. But also the core question for safety management. With the general task of safety management being to keep the system within its operating boundaries (setting aside the problem of knowing what those boundaries are) it is also core to safety management.</p>
<p>Next up the apparent paradox “Command-Adapt” is described in a contrasting description of upper-echelons view of the work and units-of-action view of the work (essentially the blunt-end/sharp-end contrasted view on work). And with that view of the work also comes a view on incidents and failures. For the blunt end:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Incidents and failures generally are diagnosed as failures of operational personnel to work-to-rule/role/plan which then leads to new pressures to conform. This is the systems architecture that underlies an emphasis on rule compliance in safety management.” (Woods, 2023, p. 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And  for the sharp end as the other side of the apparent paradox:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The central theme of the guided adaptability perspective is “plan and revise”—being poised to adapt. This perspective recognizes that disrupting events will challenge plans-in-progress, requiring adaptations, reprioritization, and reconfiguration in order to meet key goals given the effects of disturbances and changes.” (Woods, 2023, p. 4)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And with these two perspectives (“follow the plan as it describes the safe boundaries of system operations” vs “things aren’t gonna go as planned and we need to change things around”)  defined, the apparent paradox that you have to choose one or the other for how safety management is done is outlined. And then immediately uncovered as a wrong contrasting of approaches:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Empirical studies, experience, and science all reveal that the paradox is only apparent: “good” systems embedded in this universe need to plan and revise—to do both. And the necessity of both is evident in the need to manage the risk of brittleness while coping with the side effects of growth and change” (Woods, 2023, p. 5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And to me this is really the core of the paper. That this strict splitting up of two perspectives on safety management that we often see (plan-and-follow vs adapt-and-improvise, blunt-end vs sharp-end, Safety I vs. Safety II, etc) is largely the wrong question. Because we need to understand that both have their place and there needs to be an understanding of the trade-offs of when one is being employed rather than the other. And the problems arise when this isn’t recognised:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The paradox dissolves, in part, when one realizes guided adaptability depends in part on plans. The difficulty arises when organizations over-rely on plans [7]. Over-reliance undermines adaptive capacity when beyond-plan challenges arise. Beyond-plan challenges occur regularly for complex systems. The catch is: pressure to comply focuses only on the first and degrades the second.” (Woods, 2023, p. 5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In order to underline the fact that plans eventually fall short 2 classical assumptions about plans are discussed:</p>
<ol>
<li>Plans can completely specify actions</li>
<li>Rationalisations about why findings about shortcomings of plans only apply to other areas and not one’s own</li>
</ol>
<p>From the belief that the first assumption is true, it is usually derived why work-to-rule should be a guiding principle of safety management:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“If plans can fully specify actions, or nearly so, then work-to-rule/role/ plan is sufficient for productive and safe systems.” (Woods, 2023, p. 5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is the very common and alluring perspective that work is much more algorithmic rather than heuristic. This assumption that it’s possible to fully specify work also underlies for example the frequent over-eager and over-optimistic assumption of how much work can be (easily) automated (e.g. by a script or so-called “AI”).</p>
<p>Related to that assumption (and illusion) of control then rationalisations are produced of why one is in a special case and the ample findings of short comings of plans don’t apply.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The usual response from organizations to these classic findings is simple: my world is stable and not like space operations, military operations, and emergency or critical care medicine. In my world variability can be blocked or suppressed, minimizing the need for adaptation since work-to-plan/role/rule will reliably produce desired outcomes.” (Woods, 2023, p. 7)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This rationalisation according to the paper is based on several erroneous assumptions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Surprises occur rarely</li>
<li>It’s easy to know when a plan needs to be modified</li>
<li>It’s quick to put modified plans in action</li>
<li>Interdependencies are easy to limit and be analysed and modelled a-priori</li>
<li>Effects of surprise can be easily compartmentalised and contained away from interdependencies</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of these might be true for a moment but aren’t overall true throughout operation and especially lifecycle (design, growth, adaptations) of a system. And while these assumptions have been shown to be true and rediscovered over and over through research as well as experience they still  serve as a kind of feedback loop to statement 1 and the call for compliance.</p>
<p>In order then to reconcile the two apparent-paradoxical perspectives is a reconceptualisation of plans through the lens of adaptability through 4 parts:</p>
<ol>
<li>Plans are resources for action</li>
<li>Plans are necessary to recognise anomalies</li>
<li>Plans (and Automata) are competent but brittle</li>
<li>People (with the right help) provide the extra adaptive capacity to mitigate brittleness</li>
</ol>
<p>This is to recognise that plans are useful as a starting off point and a resource to grab from when action is needed, but not as a strict specification. And one very important point is that improvisation and adaptability at the sharp-end requires the pre-requisite step of detecting anomalies and deviations. This is a lot harder without a baseline of “normal” which plans can provide. In terms of automation it needs to be recognised that automation (which includes various forms of AI in their respective hype cycles as well) is competent but brittle. And that there is a persistent believe that it just needs a new push of the technology to overcome this.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Studies looking at joint systems of people and AI or operators and advanced automation revealed the fundamental brittleness of automata regardless of the underlying technology [13].” (Woods, 2023, p. 8)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And getting to the people part (which is the source of adaptive capacity) it’s very important to recognise that challenges and near-misses happen much more often than expected. And that created control systems like automation are subject to the same pressures as the systems they are supposed to control. And thus the same risk for brittleness:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“All systems are developed and operate with finite resources and live in a changing environment. As a result, plans, procedures, automation, agents, and roles are inherently limited and unable to completely cover the complexity of activities, events, and demands.” (Woods, 2023, p. 9)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And so the paper concludes on a way to perform work and safety management which is dubbed “Plan and revise: Guided Adaptability”. Which still means that there should be plans for the work to be done that are intended to be followed until it doesn’t make sense any more. The complement then is to learn from how they don’t make sense anymore and include that in the revision of plans for the future based on the best source there is for adaptations: humans.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The irony is you can only monitor how well plans fit the world by understanding how people have to adapt to fill the gaps and holes that inevitably arise as variability in the world exceeds the capability of plans and the competencies built into any system [12].” (Woods, 2023, p. 11)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And to make it clear that adaptation itself is also subject to adaptation and not some perfect state of behaviour, the following quote towards the end of the paper is extremely apt in my opinion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“You will have to establish the continuous feedback/learning loop in order to adapt how you adapt.” (Woods, 2023, p. 13)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="personal-thoughts">Personal thoughts</h2>
<p>I really liked the paper and the way it made the trade-offs of both perspectives on safety management very clear. It’s way too often the case in my opinion that a silver bullet solution is sought and once something is assumed as such, all the rest gets discarded. When in reality trade-offs and “best of both worlds” approaches to real world problems are much more likely to yield much better results. The different levels of views on the work in terms of high level planning and low level implementation also reminded me a lot of the waterfall vs agile and scheduled release vs continuous deployment discussions that are happening in technology where often one is seen as the superior approach over the other. But in reality even agile processes need longer term planning to fit into the bigger picture. And even continuous deployment means you <em>are able</em> to deploy whenever not that you have to. And sometimes planning a deploy to match the larger circumstances (outside of another teams test, maybe not on a Friday 😬, or even it can wait till the next morning) makes much more sense rather than deploying something as soon as you got the code review approved. As the famous mature engineering proverb goes</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s trade-offs all the way down</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Strategic Agility Gap: How Organizations Are Slow and Stale to Adapt in Turbulent Worlds</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/paper-strategic-agility-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/paper-strategic-agility-gap/</guid>
      <description>Key Takeaways This paper outlines how past successes drive the creation of bigger and ever more complex systems.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<p>This paper outlines how past successes drive the creation of bigger and ever more complex systems. And the risk of not being able to adapt fast enough to changing environments and systems. The gap between the adaptation possible and the adaptation required by an organisation is called “The Strategic Agility Gap” and a fundamental requirement to be able to bridge that gap is the ability to react to unplanned failure called “SNAFU catching”.</p>
<h2 id="detailed-discussion">Detailed discussion</h2>
<p>The paper approaches the topic of how organisations deal with the challenge of keeping up with an ever accelerating pace of change in environments and systems that get more and more complex. While the focus here is mostly threats and challenges in the term of surprising failures. It’s also mentioned that slow adaptability also has implications for the ability to seize opportunities. Organisations of course aren’t generally not adapting at all. They are always navigating within their range of agility to adapt to new situations. However the problem arises when this “strategic agility” as it is called in the paper isn’t enough to account for the surrounding changes (e.g. systems and environment) and provide adaptability for new challenges. The difference between the existing level of agility and the required agility to match the surrounding pace of change is what is called “the Strategic Agility Gap”:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“It is a mismatch in velocities of change and velocities of adaptation (Fig. 1)” (Woods, 2020, p. 96)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is also outlined nicely in this diagram in the paper:</p>
<p><img src="/images/reading/paper-strategic-agility-gap/diagram.png" alt="strategic agility gap diagram"></p>
<p>In order to illustrate this gap the paper discusses two cases: The 2012 Knight Capital Collapse during which an organisation wasn’t prepared to adapt to their changed environment and an incident related to “runaway” automation. And the case of large transport firms coping with the impacts and fallout of Hurricane Sandy in the same year.</p>
<p>In the case of the Knight Capital collapse a list of 5 risks are outlined that contributed to the organization’s inability to deal with the incident:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“First, small problems can interact and cascade quickly and surprisingly given the tangle of dependencies across layers inside and outside the organization. Second, as effects cascade and uncertainties grow, multiple roles struggle to understand anomalies, diagnose underlying drivers, identify compensatory actions. Third, difficulties arise getting authorization from appropriate roles to make non-routine, risky, and resource costly actions, while uncertainty remains. Fourth, all of the above take effort, time, and require coordination across roles. […] Fifth, when critical replanning decisions require serial communication vertically through the levels of the organization, responses are unable to keep pace with events.” (Woods, 2020, p. 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And in contrast the transportation firms were “poised to adapt” in the scenario they were dealing with due to constant preparatory work that preceded the incident that put them in a position to be able to quickly react:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Upper management developed mechanisms for this shift prior to particular challenge events. As hurricane Sandy approached New York, temporary teams were created quickly to provide timely updates (weather impact analysis teams).” (Woods, 2020, p. 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“These mechanisms existed because this firm’s business model, environment, clientele, and external events regularly required adaptation as surprises were a normal experience.” (Woods, 2020, p. 98)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And in contrasting the cases, the paper again emphasises the importance of being able to adapt not only within a layer of work but also vertically throughout an organisation to push decision making and coordination onto layers that allow for timely reaction to the current situation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the strategic agility gap, the challenge for organizations is to develop new forms of coordination across functional, spatial, and temporal scales—otherwise organizations will be slow, stale and fragmented as they inevitably confront surprising challenges.” (Woods, 2020, p. 99)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The paper then zooms out to a more high level view on systems and their messiness. Highlighting the fact that all development and operations of systems are limited by the fact that resources are finite. And thus preparatory vehicles like plans and automation can never cover the full extent of complexity of a given system:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“All systems are developed and operate given finite resources and live in a changing environment [5]. As a result, plans, procedures, automation, all agents and roles are inherently limited and unable to completely cover the complexity of activities, events, demands, and change” (Woods, 2020, p. 99)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a point that is also expanded upon in Woods’ 2023 paper <a href="https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/paper-command-adapt-paradox/">“Resolving the Command–Adapt Paradox: Guided Adaptability to Cope with Complexity“</a>) in greater detail to highlight the limitations of plans and automation.</p>
<p>As an essential capability in dealing with this predicament of having to quickly react to an always changing world that is only predictable in very narrow terms, Woods notes what him and Cook termed “SNFU” catching: The ability of people to adapt outside of standard plans:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“SNAFU catching, however technologically facilitated, is a fundamentally human capability essential for organizational viability […] people in some roles provide the essential adaptive capacity for SNAFU catching, though this may be local, underground, and invisible to distant perspectives [12].” (Woods, 2020, p. 99)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And with SNAFU being the normal operation, even though as the paper argues it is often rationalised away as a fringe phenomenon to put pressure on work-to-{plan,role,rule} and with that hindering the effectiveness and visibility of SNAFU catching:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The compliance pressure undermines the adaptive capacities needed for SNAFU catching (initiative), creates double binds that drive adaptations to make the system work ‘underground,’ and generates role retreat that undermines coordinated activities.” (Woods, 2020, p. 100)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the conclusion the paper then outlines a path out of the Strategic Agility Gap which is continuous adaptation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“For organizations to flourish in the gap they need to build and sustain the ability to continuously adapt.” (Woods, 2020, p. 101)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It draws on lessons from Web Operations where outages and near outages are common in a world where systems are constantly changing and due to past success are enabled to grow and change continuously. It is also a field that has and is becoming more and more important as almost every system is becoming a digital system at least in parts. And in this complex world the limitations of planning are becoming more and more apparent with the underlying layer of resilience to not have them fail catastrophically all the time is SNAFU catching:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Organizational systems succeed despite the basic limits of plans in a complex, interdependent and changing environment because responsible people adapt to make the system work despite its design—SNAFU catching. The ingredients are:” (Woods, 2020, p. 102)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>With the mentioned ingredients being:</p>
<ul>
<li>anticipation</li>
<li>contingent synchronisation</li>
<li>readiness to respond</li>
<li>proactive learning</li>
</ul>
<p>With these behaviours and properties often being severely reduced by the pressure to work-to-{plan/rule/role}, compliance, and worst the fear of sanctions when any of these expectations are violated.  And in summary:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Strategic agility gap arises as organizations’ trajectory of improvement cannot match the emergence of new challenges, risks, and opportunities as complexity penalties grow (Fig. 1). To flourish in the gap requires organizations to build and sustain capabilities for SNAFU catching.” (Woods, 2020, p. 103)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="personal-thoughts">Personal Thoughts</h2>
<p>This paper was fascinating to me in a couple of ways. But having the visual of “a gap” in the capacity and capabilities of an organisation was to me an extremely useful way of framing the problem. The paper also casually gave me the best and most succinct definition of DevOps I have ever seen in a decade or so of blog posts and talks trying to define it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Reciprocity in collaborative work is commitment to mutual assistance.” (Woods, 2020, p. 103)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Second Brain</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/building-a-second-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/building-a-second-brain/</guid>
      <description>This book was a surprisingly quick and easy read. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really sure if I was gonna like another book about taking notes (or find it useful) after reading &amp;ldquo;How To Take Smart Notes&amp;rdquo; had comparatively little practical things for me to take away from and implement in the end.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book was a surprisingly quick and easy read. I wasn&rsquo;t really sure if I was
gonna like another book about taking notes (or find it useful) after reading
<a href="/reading/how-to-take-smart-notes/">&ldquo;How To Take Smart Notes&rdquo;</a> had comparatively little practical things for me
to take away from and implement in the end. But &ldquo;Building a Second Brain&rdquo; was
very different in that regard. The book puts a lot of focus on building a
system that is very flexible and adaptable even to stressful schedules. There
are a couple of guiding principles (the PARA folder structure, refining notes
regularly, making it easy to capture notes) that are elaborated on. But there
is a lot of emphasis on making this work in even tiny moments throughout the
week. A lot of the system and ideas reminded me of bullet journaling in a way
which I&rsquo;ve been doing for years at this point and has been working very well
for me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender Trouble</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/gender-trouble/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/gender-trouble/</guid>
      <description>I don’t remember how I got to this book as I had never heard of Judith Butler before given I’ve not really had any philosophy or literature classes on a higher education level and haven’t read much about academic feminist or gender theory.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don’t remember how I got to this book as I had never heard of Judith Butler
before given I’ve not really had any philosophy or literature classes on a
higher education level and haven’t read much about academic feminist or gender
theory. So I went into this book pretty unprepared and I was immediately in for
a rude awakening. I’ve always thought of my English being pretty decent for a
second language but there were so many sentences in this book that even on the
third try I wasn’t able to grasp. The fact I haven’t read Freud, Lacan,
Foucault, or any of the other works that “Gender Trouble” discusses and bases a
lot of arguments on definitely also didn’t help. Only while I was already
somewhat deep in did I find out that Butler is somewhat notorious for having a
difficult and dense writing style. Nevertheless I stayed curious enough about
the topic to get through the book and it was definitely interesting. I had
heard of gender being a social performance before but reading it in a more
academic context and having more (albeit difficult to grasp) discussion around
it was pretty insightful for me. I don’t know if I’d recommend it unless you’re
really into the topic and have maybe read some of the referenced material. But
I don’t regret reading and struggling through it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Existential Physics</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/existential-physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/existential-physics/</guid>
      <description>I saw this book in my regular bookstore and the topic really interested me.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I saw this book in my regular bookstore and the topic really interested me. So
I started reading the book with no preconception or notion of who the author
was. Only halfway through or so I found out she also has a somewhat popular
YouTube channel.</p>
<p>Reading the book was a bit of a split for me. The author definitely does a good
job (as far as I can tell) explaining physics concepts and theories in a way
that is understandable and with the given topic in mind. And the fact that the
book is structured as chapters where each answers a specific question also
makes it a really quick and interesting read. However there have also been
parts of the book where the tone bordered on obnoxious for me with the cliche
undertone (or sometimes even explicit statement) that eventually everything can
“just” be explained with physics and how - in the author’s view - many people
(even other scientists) are incorrect in their assumptions and world views.
Which I find more jarring than entertaining. But the core idea in the book that
there are some views (e.g. the existence of a god) that are neither scientific
nor un-scientific as they can’t be proven or disproven. But rather a-scientific
as they are compatible with current science since nothing we currently know
confirms or refutes them. I’ve found this to be a really good frame for
thinking about the world. Overall I enjoyed the book with some caveats.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Existentialism?</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/what-is-existentialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/what-is-existentialism/</guid>
      <description>This was another book that I didn’t really have any expectations on when I bought it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was another book that I didn’t really have any expectations on when I
bought it. And having never really had any philosophy classes in school or
university there was definitely a certain challenge to reading this. Maybe some
of it was also the translation from French but not being used to the way
philosophers talk about topics and structure their sentences it often took me
more than reading a sentence once to understand what was being said. I don’t
think I’ve really understood what existentialism is after reading the book on a
level where I would be able to argue about it. However there were many
interesting ideas in there about what it means to live in the present and even
such grim topics like the (far) future always presenting death and how to think
about and live with that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>I had this book on my shelf since 2020 or so and never took the time to read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had this book on my shelf since 2020 or so and never took the time to read
it. With the renewed (and intensified) hype around AI this year I started to
read it even though I wasn’t sure if there was really more about machine
learning that I wanted to know and would find interesting.</p>
<p>But truth be told I really enjoyed reading this book. It’s roughly divided into
topical areas like justice, medicine, cars, and art and discusses the status
quo (as of 2020) as well as improvements and downsides to the rise of usage of
algorithms in general but also machine learning. The author takes a very
nuanced look at all these and it actually made me feel less frustrated about
using computers in some areas than I had been through the public discussions of
AI this year. Highly recommend the book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twilight of Democracy</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/twilight-of-democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/twilight-of-democracy/</guid>
      <description>Starting this book I was a little set back as the author identifies with what would have been called the “center-right” towards the late 1990s and early 2000s.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Starting this book I was a little set back as the author identifies with what
would have been called the “center-right” towards the late 1990s and early
2000s. So I wasn’t too sure where this book would be going. But I ended up
finding it super interesting. The book details some historical background as
well as current workings of politics in various countries like Poland, Hungary,
and the U.K.. There is also a lot of very personal accounts in there about how
friends of the author have drifted more towards the contemporary right and how
that feels. It was overall a pretty harrowing account of what has happened in
some countries over the past 20 years and how much similarity there is between
them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Friendships</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/big-friendship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/big-friendship/</guid>
      <description>I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what to think of this book. I generally enjoyed reading it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn&rsquo;t really know what to think of this book. I generally enjoyed reading
it. But I think I was expecting something different. I wasn’t expecting more of
a memoir of a friendship but rather thought there was some more general
discussion of the topic of friendship in there. Some parts of the book I wasn’t
super excited by as it either went into a lot of detail about social outings I
didn’t find super interesting or stopped before I felt it went to the core of
the situation.</p>
<p>Overall I liked the book. The big core message of friendship on a deep level
also takes work is something that really resonates with me. There’s too often
the message in media and entertainment that the perfect relationship (romantic
or otherwise) is effortless, which does us all a disservice as we assume we
don’t have to put the work in. But this book talks very clearly about the work
being part of a friendship and I really liked that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The book you wish your parents had read</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/book-you-wish-your-parents-had-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/book-you-wish-your-parents-had-read/</guid>
      <description>I liked a lot how the book always came back to talking to the kids and empathizing with their emotions instead of trying to abolish them.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I liked a lot how the book always came back to talking to the kids and
empathizing with their emotions instead of trying to abolish them. And there
were always good examples that came with every section to illustrate the
point. However it still felt very &ldquo;good weather parenting&rdquo; advice to me, in
the sense that it talks about how to do these things when you have the time to
take for it. But there was hardly anything in there about how to deal with
situations where time is tight or there isn&rsquo;t the space to slow down and
prolong the situation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving Mathematical Problems: A Personal Perspective</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/solving-mathematical-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/solving-mathematical-problems/</guid>
      <description>It was fun to read through this book and see different approaches to solving the problems presented.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was fun to read through this book and see different approaches to solving
the problems presented. I didn&rsquo;t follow through all the proofs and steps all
the time because I would have needed to carefully do it with pen and paper and
that was really the mood I was in when I wanted to read. But it made me miss
school math and solving problems a lot. It also ended up being a bit hard to
follow for me occasionally as I read the book in English and most of my math
education was in German. So there were definitely words and terms I wasn&rsquo;t
familiar with at all. Overall I enjoyed reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Survival Guide</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/black-hole-survival-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/black-hole-survival-guide/</guid>
      <description>I absolutely enjoyed this book and devoured it in 2 days or so.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I absolutely enjoyed this book and devoured it in 2 days or so. Janna Levin has a fantastically fun and entertaining way to talk about the most fascinating things. And black holes sure are fascinating. There were a lot of parts in the book where I was sure I&rsquo;m not getting quite the importance of the implications she explained. Or even the science on the highest of levels. But I enjoy thinking about space. And the book did exactly that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s not about the Burqa</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/not-about-the-burqa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/not-about-the-burqa/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed this book. Mostly because I rarely have read any texts, let alone feminist ones from a Muslim women perspective.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed this book. Mostly because I rarely have read any texts, let alone feminist ones from a Muslim women perspective. There&rsquo;s a lot of things I learned having previously had close to no knowledge of Islam, its traditions, or which are practiced. The book is very UK centric as most of the essay authors live there. So I&rsquo;m curious to also read more from authors from other places.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking, Fast and Slow</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/thinking-fast-and-slow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/thinking-fast-and-slow/</guid>
      <description>I had originally started reading this on my Kindle in 2016 but quickly abandoned it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had originally started reading this on my Kindle in 2016 but quickly abandoned it. I then thought it was because I didn&rsquo;t find the book too interesting but I found out some time later that I just didn&rsquo;t enjoy reading on the Kindle much. So having moved to reading exclusively on paper over the last couple of years, I gave the book another try this year and absolutely enjoyed it. There&rsquo;s a lot of fascinating facts and insights into research in there. And a lot of examples to try out yourself to realize that your own brain works the same way. I took a lot of notes for this one and can definitely recommend it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven Brief Lessons on Physics</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/seven-brief-lessons-on-physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/seven-brief-lessons-on-physics/</guid>
      <description>I really liked the book. It was short and digestible but interesting and fun to read nonetheless.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really liked the book. It was short and digestible but interesting and fun to read nonetheless. I think I probably have read about most of the seven things somewhere else before (which doesn&rsquo;t mean I understood or have a good grasp on them). So it wasn&rsquo;t mind blowing new things I was reading. But Rovelli has a very philosophical style how he talks about these things which makes it really enjoyable.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Order of Time</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-order-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-order-of-time/</guid>
      <description>I went into this book expecting much more physics than what was actually in there.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I went into this book expecting much more physics than what was actually in there. There was definitely a lot of explanation of concepts on a high level. But overall the book felt much more on the philosophy side of things. Which - after realizing and getting used to it - I really liked. The thing I struggled with was the fact that so much is explained via entropy in the book. And entropy has always been a hard topic for me to wrap my brain around. Even in university. So there were some parts that left me more confused than I would have liked. Due to no fault of the author.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The End of Everything</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-end-of-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-end-of-everything/</guid>
      <description>This was an absolutely wonderful and mind blowing book to read.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was an absolutely wonderful and mind blowing book to read. I had to think a lot of “Dark Matter and the Dinosaurs” while reading it. I feared at first that it would be too depressing. But the author has an absolutely enjoyable writing style and it made the whole topic fun and interesting rather than loom and doom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Statistics: How to learn from Data</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-statistics/</guid>
      <description>It took me a while to get through this book which had less to do with the book itself and more with how I was able to make time to read.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It took me a while to get through this book which had less to do with the book itself and more with how I was able to make time to read. So the first couple of chapters were spread out for me over a couple of weeks and thus I had a hard time getting into it. But once I managed to make proper time to read continuously I really enjoyed the flow of the book. It’s much less mathematical than I assumed beforehand. But it’s really well written and does a good job explaining statistical concepts in plain English. And I really appreciated the strong focus on the fact that (good) statistics is more than just applying some formulas but also a hard look at whether the data and the conclusions make sense for the questions that need to be answered.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/four-thousand-weeks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/four-thousand-weeks/</guid>
      <description>I read this book after I had one friend really enjoy it and another one finding the audio book pretty insufferable.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read this book after I had one friend really enjoy it and another one finding the audio book pretty insufferable. Which is an interesting combination to say the least. Overall I did enjoy the book a lot. Even though I could definitely see the preachy and more annoying parts of it. The general message of the books is that we don’t actually have that many weeks, so it’s worth it to think about how to spend them. What kind of things actually are enjoyable (of the things that we do voluntarily) and which things we can more or less do away with.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cancer Journals</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-cancer-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-cancer-journals/</guid>
      <description>I found this book while browsing through the local book store.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found this book while browsing through the local book store. And I found it really intriguing because even though cancer seems to be everywhere and all around us in some ways and I&rsquo;ve had a number of friends and family suffer through and even die of cancer, it&rsquo;s not something I&rsquo;ve personally experienced. Especially not going through a mastectomy as a black, queer woman in the 70s. So I was interested in reading a personal account of something that I will never actually experience myself. And I&rsquo;m very glad I did. Lorde talks very directly and openly about the struggle she went through, the adversaries she faced, as well as the things that helped her through. I can very much recommend reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Der Russe ist einer, der Birken liebt</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/russe-der-birken-liebt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/russe-der-birken-liebt/</guid>
      <description>I decided to read this book after I had read Die Macht der Mehrsprachigkeit by the same author earlier this year.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I decided to read this book after I had read <a href="https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/macht-der-mehrsprachigkeit/">Die Macht der Mehrsprachigkeit</a> by the same author earlier this year. I haven&rsquo;t read a lot of German literature (let alone fiction) since I was in school for no real reason. So I was curious about some more contemporary authors. And the book really wasn&rsquo;t an easy read. It&rsquo;s a very emotional and not often happy story and deals with a lot of heavy topics around war, migration, loss, and what it means to be and have a home. Nonetheless I flew through its nearly 300 pages in about 2 days. And I was sad when I was done as I wanted to keep reading.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afropean</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/afropean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/afropean/</guid>
      <description>This was an absolutely fascinating book to read. For every city that the author visits throughout the book and talks to people I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to see them (and I&amp;rsquo;ve been to a good chunk of them) in a new light.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was an absolutely fascinating book to read. For every city that the
author visits throughout the book and talks to people I&rsquo;ve learned to see them
(and I&rsquo;ve been to a good chunk of them) in a new light. And made me reflect
about a lot of things. I can whole-heartedly recommend this book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Error</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/human-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/human-error/</guid>
      <description>It took me quite a while to get through this book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It took me quite a while to get through this book. I had actually abandoned it before and then came back to it. It&rsquo;s very theoretical and academic (even though it contains some suggestions towards more practical applications of the theory towards the end). There is a lot of interesting thought in there about how to put something more concrete to the notion of errors or mistakes. And even if most of it is now superseded it provides interesting insight into the research of human error during that time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Choice and Invidual Values</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/social-choice-individual-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/social-choice-individual-values/</guid>
      <description>Given this book is more or less the printed and published version of Arrow&amp;rsquo;s PhD.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Given this book is more or less the printed and published version of Arrow&rsquo;s PhD. thesis, it is not an easy read. It lays the foundation and explanation for his <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow%27s_impossibility_theorem">Impossibility Theorem</a> which states limitations of a ranked voting electoral systems when it comes to individual and communal preferences. I can&rsquo;t claim to have understood all of it fully. It was nevertheless very interesting to me, so read something from a field I have hardly any experience or knowledge in. I started reading it earlier in the year and then put it down because I didn&rsquo;t have the brain space to get into the math and proofs of it. And then I picked it back up during the time of the German general election this year. I found it really interesting to read about how these kind of problems are described and reasoned about in political and economical academia. And which kind of definitions and trade offs are being chosen to create a system within these formal proofs can exist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bilingual Brain</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-bilingual-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-bilingual-brain/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed reading this book. For years at this point I&amp;rsquo;ve felt like a bilingual in German and English, and I&amp;rsquo;ve come across so many situations where I unconsciously chose one language over the other.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed reading this book. For years at this point I&rsquo;ve felt like a bilingual in German and English, and I&rsquo;ve come across so many situations where I unconsciously chose one language over the other. And then was surprised by it. I&rsquo;ve always wondered how bilingualism or multilingualism is reflected in the brain and how it&rsquo;s different between people and languages. &ldquo;The Bilingual Brain&rdquo; gives a ton of insight into the research field of multilingulism as well as highlighting the approaches, challenges, and limitations of research in this field. There were many situation in the book, when a common pattern for bilinguals was explained, where I was happy to realize it&rsquo;s something I do to.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between the World and Me</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/between-the-world-and-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/between-the-world-and-me/</guid>
      <description>This was an absolutely fantastic, emotional, gut-wrenching, sad, and happy book to read.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was an absolutely fantastic, emotional, gut-wrenching, sad,  and happy book to read. I&rsquo;ve come to really like the way it is written, as a conversation between the author and his son, trying to explain the world. There&rsquo;s a lot of mixing of history, current affairs, personal history and memories, which makes for a very personal piece of literature.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Zettelkasten: Principles, Methods, &amp; Examples</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-zettelkasten/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-zettelkasten/</guid>
      <description>I read this as I was working on figuring out how to set up my Zettelkasten and how it would best serve me after reading the basics of the theory behind it in How to Take Smart Notes.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read this as I was working on figuring out how to set up my Zettelkasten and
how it would best serve me after reading the basics of the theory behind it in
<a href="../how-to-take-smart-notes">How to Take Smart Notes</a>. And there sadly
wasn&rsquo;t much new stuff in the book that I haven&rsquo;t already read in various forms
in some blog posts over the last couple of months. However it was really nice
to have this information all in one place in book form. And get the
confirmation that I am on the right track with how I&rsquo;m building my
Zettelkasten. Or at least going in the same direction that has worked for
others so far as well.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Do Nothing: Resisting the Attention Economy</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-to-do-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-to-do-nothing/</guid>
      <description>This was one of those books that I started reading with a lot of expectations that it would be similar to Digital Minimalism and tell me a lot of things that I already kinda knew.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was one of those books that I started reading with a lot of expectations
that it would be similar to <a href="../digital-minimalism">Digital Minimalism</a>
and tell me a lot of things that I already kinda knew. But I was completely
surprised by it. The book is much more about what to do <em>instead</em> of following
the pull of the attention economy, rather than why it&rsquo;s bad. There is some of
that in there as well of course. However the fascinating part of the book is
much more the fact that it kinda acts like a nice guide about how to re-engage
with your physical surroundings, your city, countryside, and neighborhood. The
real things around you. It took me a while to realize that and read the book
with that in mind. And I definitely struggled early on as there was way more
talk about the dropout communities of the 70s that I really was interested in.
But after finishing the book I definitely have a new-found appreciation of my
neighborhood and the nature around me. It was a very positive read and in the
end not really about &ldquo;doing nothing&rdquo;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Macht der Mehrsprachigkeit - Über Herkunft und Vielfalt</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/macht-der-mehrsprachigkeit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/macht-der-mehrsprachigkeit/</guid>
      <description>The book ended up being a super fascinating read about how language and multilingualism is viewed in Germany.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The book ended up being a super fascinating read about how language and
multilingualism is viewed in Germany. I&rsquo;ve found myself reminded of a lot of
things that I&rsquo;ve noticed since living abroad in the US and coming back to
Germany. And it gave me a new sense of reality of what it means to arrive and
live in Germany as someone who&rsquo;s first language isn&rsquo;t German and isn&rsquo;t
considered one of the &ldquo;good&rdquo; languages either.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Limits of Organization (Fels Lectures on Public Policy Analysis)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/limits-of-organizations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/limits-of-organizations/</guid>
      <description>This was a very fascinating book. In part because I have never really attended an economics lecture.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was a very fascinating book. In part because I have never really attended
an economics lecture. And the ones I did were geared towards very practical
things that we had to learn by hard. So while reading this book I was at the
same time getting used to thinking about economic things in a theoretical
context and taking in the information conveyed in the text. I enjoyed it a lot
and took a lot of inspiration and food for thought from it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Altered Traits</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/altered-traits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/altered-traits/</guid>
      <description>I went into this book with a lot of expectations. I was very curious about the science behind meditation and how to approach the topic in a scientific way.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I went into this book with a lot of expectations. I was very curious about the
science behind meditation and how to approach the topic in a scientific way.
While ultimately that information was in the book to some extent, it overall
wasn&rsquo;t what I had hoped it would be. First of all there is <em>a lot</em> of
namedropping happening. So for a quite some time I was busy with going back to
re-read who someone was, or wondering whether I should care to remember that
person&rsquo;s name because it would be important later on. This is likely very
interesting to someone who is already familiar with well-known people in the
field of meditation but was mostly distracting for me. The tl;dr for the book
seems to be that there are still more questions than answers about the science
behind meditation and how to explain the clearly visible benefits with a lot
of long time practitioners. But to me that could have been a blog post and not
such a long book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Emotions Are Made: The Secret Life of the Brain</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-emotions-are-made/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-emotions-are-made/</guid>
      <description>This was an absolutely mind blowing read in the sense that it made me think about a lot of things in a new light.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was an absolutely mind blowing read in the sense that it made me think about a lot of things in a new light. The book is an introduction into [the theory of constructed emotion] which has been the author’s field of research for many years. The tl;dr kinda being that emotions don’t just exist as objective reality but are constructed by humans as we interpret external and internal sensor input.</p>
<p>The author makes it very clear how much research has gone into the theory and how it explains many observations that can’t be explained by the classical view on emotions. It’s definitely a theory that’s a lot less intuitive than the classical view, but I’ve still found myself nodding along at some passages, while being very perplexed at others trying to understand concepts like simulation and prediction of the brain. And what it means for my day to day perceptions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to take smart notes</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-to-take-smart-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/how-to-take-smart-notes/</guid>
      <description>I really like this book even though it’s fairly academic to a large extent.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really like this book even though it’s fairly academic to a large extent. I’ve heard about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten" title="Zettelkasten on Wikipedia">Zettelkasten method</a> quite a bit especially recently and I was very curious to learn more about it. Coming to the book with that context, I didn’t mind the academic style of the book too much. However it’s definitely more a book that makes you reflect on how you want to take notes and why more than giving you a concrete guide on what to do.</p>
<p>After finishing the book I took some time to think about how a Zettelkasten style note taking setup would best fit into my day to day. And how I would want to interact with such a setup. And I’m still in the process of moving my old notes into the system and figuring out how it works out for me. So while I can’t say anything yet about how effective the things are that I learned through the book, I found it intriguing enough to make me adapt the method and try it out.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Born a Crime</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/born-a-crime/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/born-a-crime/</guid>
      <description>I bought this book never really having watched any of Trevor Noah’s comedy or The Daily Show with him.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I bought this book never really having watched any of Trevor Noah’s comedy or The Daily Show with him. But the book sounded really intriguing to me and I was curious about his life and background. And the book was absolutely fantastic. It’s one of the few books I’ve read where I literally laughed out lout while also being struck and deeply emotional reading through other parts. I&rsquo;ve only been to South Africa for a couple of days and only really been to Cape Town. So I’ve had (and still have) very limited knowledge of the history of the country. And the book taught me a ton about what it was like growing up during and after Apartheid and how kids can perceive very extreme and cruel situations. This is definitely one of the best books I’ve read and I can wholeheartedly recommend picking it up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outlining your Novel: Map Your Way to Success</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/outlining-your-novel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/outlining-your-novel/</guid>
      <description>I picked this book up because I’ve always been interested in outlining.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I picked this book up because I’ve always been interested in outlining. But even more so I’ve fascinated by how many people are fans of outlining. To the point where there are discussion about things like “is OmniOutliner or OneNote the better outlining app” and the point that there are even dedicated outlining apps. I’ve mostly done outlining for my writing with bullet points in a plain text or markdown file. And I wanted to know if I’m missing anything. In addition to that I also find the process of writing a book or novel super fascinating. I don’t know if I would want to write one. But the process of planning, structuring, and writing something of that size I find very interesting and fascinating. And I wanted to see if I could learn something from it for shorter writing like documentation and blog posts.</p>
<p>The book is structured in a way where only the first two chapters are really about outlining itself. The advantages of writing an outline versus writing “at the seat of your pants” as well as different approaches to outlines (e.g. mind maps, longform writing, bullet points) are discussed.</p>
<p>The following chapters then are a whirlwind tour through planning a novel and how to apply outlining to areas like plot planning, character development, or creating a backstory. At the end of every chapter there is an interview with a writer about the value and their approach in outlining.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed reading the book. I learned a lot about structuring my writing and what kind of things go into planning a novel. It’s very accessibly written and the chapters all have a good length so it never feels like they are dragged out or missing content. I could have done without the writer interviews as they didn’t really add a lot to the book but had a couple of interesting anecdotes. I don’t know if there would be anything new for a seasoned author in the book, but I can definitely recommend it as a quick intro into planning a novel.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1919</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/1919/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/1919/</guid>
      <description>I was interested in Eve Ewing’s writing ever since I read her run on Marvel’s Ironheart.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was interested in Eve Ewing’s writing ever since I read her run on Marvel’s Ironheart. So I got her other books a couple of months ago as well. I started with &ldquo;1919&rdquo; and it was definitely an interesting albeit completely new experience for me. I&rsquo;ve not really read poetry since school where I wasn&rsquo;t a big fan because it always felt forced. But while reading &ldquo;1919&rdquo; I definitely regretted not paying more attention in school to be able to pick up on the stylistic and technique choices in the book. &ldquo;1919&rdquo; is a collection of poems with the background of an official report about the 1919 race riots in Chicago which I had never heard of until I read the book. It was absolutely educational to read the various passages from the report that were the basis for the poem. And then get an emotional and very personal feeling poem about the passage right after. Given my own lack of knowledge about poetry I constantly felt like I was missing some fascinating nuances about the writing. And I&rsquo;ve started learning more about poetry and creative writing to rectify that. And I definitely plan to re-read &ldquo;1919&rdquo; once I&rsquo;m more knowledgeable about poetry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Draw People Every Day: Short Lessons in Portrait and Figure Drawing Using Ink and Color</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/draw-people-every-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/draw-people-every-day/</guid>
      <description>This book caught my eye while I was browsing for art books.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book caught my eye while I was browsing for art books. I’ve been trying
for a while to incorporate (almost) daily drawing back into my daily schedule.
But in a lighter weight way with less pressure to do finished pieces. And “Draw
People Every Day” definitely fit the bill for that. The book provides a great
high level overview for getting started with ink drawing and dives deeper into
various topics like e.g. the importance of drawing from life, gesture drawing
and how to achieve different effects with line weights. The same approach is
then taken in the final chapter to talk about using color for quick sketching.</p>
<p>After having spent a lot of time on learning how to draw in the last 2 years,
there weren’t a lot of things that were really new to me in this book. However
it’s the book I wish I had 2 years ago when I got started. It does a great job
laying down the fundamentals for getting started with sketching. And it
definitely inspired me to do more quick sketching and drawing from life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter and the Dinosaurs: The Astounding Interconnectedness of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dark-matter-and-the-dinosaurs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dark-matter-and-the-dinosaurs/</guid>
      <description>I had heard about this book on several occasions and when we went to the natural history museum here in Berlin I found it in the shop and decided to finally buy it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had heard about this book on several occasions and when we went to the natural history museum here in Berlin I found it in the shop and decided to finally buy it. I didn’t really know what to expect but having recently read a couple of popular science books about physics I was very intrigued. And the book did definitely deliver, albeit in a very different way than I thought. I went into reading it with the expectation that the majority of the book would be about dark matter and its details. This however is really only a small part of the whole book. Throughout the book there are detailed explanations about the (presumed) origins of life, the makeup of the cosmos, mass extinctions, determining the age of rocks, history of scientific discoveries and methods, dinosaurs, impact crater anatomy, why Pluto isn’t a planet anymore, why meteroids as we call them often aren’t really meteroids, and much more. At the end of the book the author then circles back to dark matter and some of the recent theories and discoveries, tying all of the chapters together.</p>
<p>I have to admit that occasionally while reading the book I was fascinated by the things I was learning while at the same time not really knowing what it has to do with dark matter. Nevertheless I extremely enjoyed this book and the things I learned reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerate: Building and Scaling High-Performing Technology Organizations</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/accelerate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/accelerate/</guid>
      <description>This book has come up in various discussions again and again since its release so I finally decided to read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book has come up in various discussions again and again since its release so I finally decided to read it. I wasn’t sure what to think of it going in, having worked a lot in &ldquo;DevOps settings&rdquo; before.</p>
<p>There is a ton of really good stuff in this book. If you’re looking for an introduction into how to build a high performance engineering culture, and which things to focus on, then this is definitely a book that will help you and guide you in the right direction. And the big take away from the book is that there are 4 software delivery performance measures to focus on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lead Time</li>
<li>Deployment Frequency</li>
<li>Mean Time to Restore (MTTR)</li>
<li>Change Fail Percentage</li>
</ul>
<p>Unfortunately not a lot of what is in the book was new to me. Which is why it felt like a bit of a drag to me to get through it. And I personally also had some problems with the very prescriptive style of the findings. The longer I work in technology the more I tend to gravitate towards &ldquo;it depends&rdquo; on most things. Like deployment frequency is so highly correlated to the development process and whether or not there are actually features to be written that it’s really hard to just say more deployments always means better.</p>
<p>I really appreciated the inclusion of the research methodology in such detail in the book. That was the part where a ton was new to me and I really learned a couple of things about how to extract data from surveys.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sapiens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sapiens/</guid>
      <description>Usually I tend to shy away from longer (i.e. over 300 pages) books because I feel like I’m a somewhat slow reader.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Usually I tend to shy away from longer (i.e. over 300 pages) books because I
feel like I’m a somewhat slow reader. And it takes me too long to get through
and I feel demotivated to pick the book up. Sapiens still really piqued my
interest and it absolutely delivered.</p>
<p>The overall book is structured in chapters about the cognitive revolution, the
agricultural revolution, the unification of humankind, and the scientific
revolution. I’ve never thought about historical periods in that way and it was
interesting to see them presented in that way. The book covers the usual things
like evolution of Homo Sapiens with a bigger brain than other species, the
early periods as hunter gatherers, the emergence of agricultural and the
connected settling down.</p>
<p>The book also discusses cultural things like a common belief (e.g. religion or
capitalism) being a necessary establishment to allow for communication (and
collaboration to some extent) across larger territories than just family or
tribe boundaries. For any evolutionary step the trade-offs in those changes are
also discussed. Especially the cruel(-er) aspects of human dominance on the
planet.</p>
<p>I learned a lot reading this book and it definitely made me think about history
and human evolution from other perspectives than usual.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/drive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/drive/</guid>
      <description>I really liked especially the first part of the book that focuses on the science and research of motivation.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really liked especially the first part of the book that focuses on the
science and research of motivation. It was very interesting to read about the
history of behavioral psychology and how in various stages scientists ran
different experiments to understand the psychology of motivation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Wikipedia’s triumph seems to defy the laws of behavioral physics</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the more prominent examples of intrinsic motivation in the book is
contribution to open source. At that part it shows that the book was written
over 10 years ago. Because the discussion of open source is solely focused on
the positive effects of honing skills, furthering one’s career through the
work, and the intrinsic “feel good” motivation of giving back and contributing.
However over the last 10 years the problem of burn out with open source
maintainers has become a major topic that is completely absent here. And there
is also no real acknowledgement of maintainers vs contributors and the
difference in demand, work, and rewards. But I don’t think that detracts from
the points the book is making, merely something I immediately jumped to when
reading these packages as some missing nuance in the argument.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; rewards can perform a weird sort of behavioral alchemy: They can transform an interesting task into a drudge. They can turn play into work</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Large parts of the book then deal with the detrimental effects of the “carrot
and stick” approach to management. It was interesting to read about flow state,
rewards, and how - depending on how they are used - they can be actually
detrimental to motivation. This part contained an interesting short lesson in
management history and that the idea of creating space for autonomy for workers
has come up a couple of times in the past but never got a lot of traction. And
that the new way of granting autonomy and letting workers have more urgency
over their work is improving motivation. However there are also a couple of
dangerous ideas the author arrives at. That can easily be read as management
being a problem, rather than the fact that it is a craft that needs to honed
just as any other work</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps management is one of the forces that’s switching our default setting and <em>producing</em> that state [of passive inertia]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally there is a discussion about mastery and putting effort into something
that I found very interesting based on Carol Dweck’s - a psychology professor
at Stanford - research. The discussion of mastery being a mindset rather than a
set goal resonated a lot with me. Especially the idea that intelligence is not
a set entity within people but a resource that can be increased via learning.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That is the nature of mastery: Mastery is a mindset</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And finally the idea that mastery is an infinite pursuit. That even if you
spend a lifetime doing something, you can never truly master something. There
will always be more to learn, more to practice, more to &hellip; master.</p>
<p>Overall I really enjoyed the book. Even though there are definitely parts that
haven’t aged quite so well over the last 10 years and with all the things we’ve
learned from tech startups left and right misunderstanding the importance of
structure, management, and Human Resources. There were many parts that I really
enjoyed reading and learned a bunch of things from.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics and Philosophy: The Revolution in Modern Science</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/physics-and-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/physics-and-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>This book was just plain amazing. I didn’t know what to expect when I found this at the book store and I was reading books about (quantum) physics at the time, so I was curious to see that Heisenberg had written a book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book was just plain amazing. I didn’t know what to expect when I found this at the book store and I was reading books about (quantum) physics at the time, so I was curious to see that Heisenberg had written a book. A lot of the (quantum) physics details went over my head. But I loved the discussion of its implications on &ldquo;reality&rdquo; and the philosophy of being. It’s an extremely dense read but I got so much out of it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Aid for your Child&#39;s Mind: Simple steps to soothe anxiety, fears and worries</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/first-aid-for-your-childs-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/first-aid-for-your-childs-mind/</guid>
      <description>I also found this one by accident while looking through the book store.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I also found this one by accident while looking through the book store. It was interesting to read a psychologist’s view on dealing with anxiety in kids. And it turned out to be much more interesting and useful for its explanations of general behaving towards children. The exercises are a bit too involved for me to want to try them. But I can see them being useful.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weisse Nächte (Vollständige Deutsche Ausgabe)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/weisse-naechte/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/weisse-naechte/</guid>
      <description>I decided to give this book a try after poking around at the local book store.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I decided to give this book a try after poking around at the local book store. I realized I’ve never read a single Dostoyevsky. And I sure wasn’t gonna read “War &amp; Peace” just to give it a try and see how I like it. After some quick googling it seemed like “Weiße Nächte” was one of his fairly popular works, and they had it in the <a href="(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reclam">Reclam</a> version which is about 4 Euros. So not a huge investment.</p>
<p>So I read the whole thing with not a lot of expectations. And overall I didn’t hate it. It was slightly obnoxious at times, and Dostoyevsky seems to definitely have a thing for drama. Plus it has all the problems you can expect from a man during the 19th century when it comes to respecting women. The ending made up for a lot though.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Field Guide to Getting Lost</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-field-guide-to-getting-lost/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-field-guide-to-getting-lost/</guid>
      <description>This was another purchase while rummaging at the book store. I&amp;rsquo;ve read Solnit‘s „Men explain things to me&amp;quot; a couple of years ago.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was another purchase while rummaging at the book  store. I&rsquo;ve read Solnit‘s „Men explain things to me&quot; a couple of years ago. And since I really enjoyed that one, I wanted to read another one of her works. I&rsquo;m not usually one for essays so it was definitely a different experience from reading more science related books.</p>
<p>I thoroughly enjoyed reading „A Field Guide to Getting Lost&quot; even though (or maybe because of?) I often found myself getting lost myself in an essay and wondering what&rsquo;s the point she&rsquo;s trying to bring across. It was also at times deeply emotional to read for me as I was reminded of personal loss (or the fear of it) with many of her essays.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-minimalism/</guid>
      <description>It took me quite a while after buying this book to find the excitement to actually read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It took me quite a while after buying this book to find the excitement to actually read it. Which had nothing to do with the book itself but the fact that I was already sold on the concept of &ldquo;Digital Minimalism&rdquo; and thought there wouldn’t be new or interesting things for me in there.</p>
<p>However once I started reading the book I immediately got sucked in and really enjoyed it. The book is very well researched and there are a lot of references to other works and research that are interesting to follow up on. It also contains a good mix of background information and actionable things to do for minimizing digital factors in once life. That makes it really easy (and somewhat also creates the desire to try) to give the exercises for minimization a spin.</p>
<p>My fear of already being sold on the concept and thus the book feeling like preaching to me as the choir were completely unfounded. If anything I got a confirmation and reaffirmation to my own practices of minimizing digital influences on my life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Logic in an Illogical World</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-logic/</guid>
      <description>This book gives a thorough introduction into logic and how to apply it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book gives a thorough introduction into logic and how to apply it. And I really enjoyed the discussion of what kind of things can be applied, how to build a logical structure and argument, and what the limits of a logical argument are.</p>
<p>I especially enjoyed the discussions of axioms as a kind of personal value system. And thus the root of any logical reasoning that you apply to arguments. This was the part for me that really tied the theoretical approach of logic and the emotional and moral foundations of one’s own beliefs together.</p>
<p>Overall however I wanted this book to be better. While I really enjoyed the logic part, there was one thing that made it really hard for me to get into a flow while reading. The author kept jumping between theory and examples way too frequently for my taste. She also rarely used lighter &ldquo;introductory&rdquo; examples. But most of the time jumped straight into heavy examples around racism, sexism, and other topics like that. Which made it much harder for me to get an understanding of the logical foundations as I was trying to keep the theoretical ideas in my head while also dealing with the emotional reaction to such heavy examples. I don’t think that those didn’t have a part in the book at all, but rather for me it would have worked better to reserve these heavy examples for the end. At which point I had familiarized myself with the concepts that got introduced, had some simple examples to apply them, and could focus on a more trying example as a completion of the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Watercolor Artist&#39;s Bible</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-watercolor-bible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-watercolor-bible/</guid>
      <description>A while into learning how to draw I realized that watercolor is a lot more fun and versatile than I thought it was from my experience using it in art class in school.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A while into learning how to draw I realized that watercolor is a lot more fun and versatile than I thought it was from my experience using it in art class in school. So I researched around and found this book recommended as a sort of reference book for watercolor artists. And it’s exactly that. The book gives a great overview over all the different aspects and techniques of using watercolor. Reading it gave me a much better understanding of the medium and I still refer back to it to look some things up occasionally.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Briefer History of Time</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-briefer-history-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-briefer-history-of-time/</guid>
      <description>I decided to read this new edition of &amp;ldquo;A Brief History of Time&amp;rdquo;, which I had started but never finished.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I decided to read this new edition of &ldquo;A Brief History of Time&rdquo;, which I had started but never finished. I really enjoyed it even though most of it went totally over my head. I read this book on the Kindle and mostly before going to sleep. Which is not a good combination for reading a book with such an intense topic. I bought it a second time as a paperback and will probably reread it on paper some time soon.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sketch Every Day: 100&#43; simple drawing exercises from Simone Grünewald</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sketch-every-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sketch-every-day/</guid>
      <description>I absolutely loved this book. It was more of a flip through and reading individual chapters for me than a book I read front to back.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I absolutely loved this book. It was more of a flip through and reading individual chapters for me than a book I read front to back. The chapters cover the author’s creative journey, some general advice for artists, art fundamentals, character design, and even a chapter on managing a family life while also making time and space for art. Every chapter and its sub sections contain a ton of very helpful examples. All drawn in Simone Grünewald’s well known style. So it’s easy to see how to approach faces, noses, hair, old and young people. And even flora and fauna.</p>
<p>The whole book is absolutely fun to read and I can highly recommend it for learning and inspiration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee Nerd: How to Have Your Coffee and Drink It Too</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/coffee-nerd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/coffee-nerd/</guid>
      <description>Really enjoyed the book. I’ve been nerding out on coffee for a couple of years now and I’ve definitely learned a bunch of new things through the book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Really enjoyed the book. I’ve been nerding out on coffee for a couple of years now and I’ve definitely learned a bunch of new things through the book. And it’s absolutely entertainingly written. Definitely recommended if you’re into coffee.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calm Technology: Designing for Billions of Devices and the Internet of Things</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/calm-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/calm-technology/</guid>
      <description>I was pretty excited about this book. I used to follow Amber Case on social media and she did some interesting early IoT stuff.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was pretty excited about this book. I used to follow Amber Case on social media and she did some interesting early IoT stuff. But the book overall is written with mostly anecdotal examples and not many directly practical things. It also has some confusing layout quirks that occasionally makes it hard to read. But content wise it&rsquo;s pretty good if you’re new to the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tree of Yoga</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-tree-of-yoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-tree-of-yoga/</guid>
      <description>I didn’t much enjoy the book which might be due to expecting something different.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn’t much enjoy the book which might be due to expecting something different. I didn’t have strong expectation but I wanted to get some more background on where yoga is coming from and what else is part of it to enhance my own yoga (and maybe meditation) practice. And I’ve definitely learned a couple of things from the book. But those could have been summarized on 10 pages. The rest of the time I’ve felt the book to mostly be repetitive, rambling, almost condescending at times, and even occasionally dangerously wrong (e.g. there’s a section in which it’s said that inverted poses while menstruating can lead to cancer).</p>
<p>There are definitely good things in there about balance, not seeing yoga practice as a competition, listening to your body, taking time, etc. But as a fairly scientific person it’s hard to read over the parts where the last 100 years of modern medicine are ignored.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slack: Getting Past Burnout, Busywork, and the Myth of Total Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/slack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/slack/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed this book. As someone who has not been actively part of the dotcom era, and has mostly been told about the bad sides of that time, it’s refreshing to read something coming out of that time full of what are still essentially progressive ideas today.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed this book. As someone who has not been actively part of the dotcom era, and has mostly been told about the bad sides of that time, it’s refreshing to read something coming out of that time full of what are still essentially progressive ideas today. Slack as the part of the work where innovation happens vs the always on, always busy culture is something organizations can still learn heaps from today. Definitely recommend reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Oneself (Harvard Business Review Classics)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/managing-oneself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/managing-oneself/</guid>
      <description>It’s really short, more of an essay really, so there’s no reason not to read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s really short, more of an essay really, so there’s no reason not to read it. It gives a couple of really good and fairly practical tips about what to find out about oneself in order to be effective and successful.</p>
<p>One of the things that definitely did strike me as interesting were Drucker’s points about taking notes and writing things down in general:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If I don’t write it down immediately, I forget it right away. If I put it into a sketch book, I never forget it and I never have to look it up again</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve had this experience so frequently, especially as a kid in school. That when I wrote something down (e.g. homework for the day) I rarely needed to look it up again but remembered what I had to do. Because I would also often remember it either way, I sadly drew the wrong conclusion there (namely that writing things down isn’t worth the hassle). Which stifled my note taking skills and a lot of my learning later on. It wasn’t until a couple of years ago that I realized that it was precisely that process of writing things down that made me memorize my homework.</p>
<p>A good part of the book also is about figuring out which version of yourself you want to be. Which I think is a really important aspect of maturing as a person and figuring out why you’re even trying to get better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That is the mirror test. Ethics requires that you ask yourself, what kind of person do I want to see in the mirror in the morning?</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technically Wrong: Sexist Apps, Biased Algorithms, and Other Threats of Toxic Tech</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/technically-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/technically-wrong/</guid>
      <description>This is a fantastic book. It walks through many different facets of how interfaces are causing people to have a hard time instead of being useful.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a fantastic book. It walks through many different facets of how interfaces are causing people to have a hard time instead of being useful. And looks at many different factors contributing to the status quo. I’ve definitely spent a lot of time educating myself on the topic before and while some things I already knew about, the book provided a great mix of new information, different view points, and reminders for myself. I wholeheartedly recommend this to anyone working in tech.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resilient Management</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/resilient-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/resilient-management/</guid>
      <description>I’ve known Lara for years and have also been part of her organization for a bit when we worked at Etsy together.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve known Lara for years and have also been part of her organization for a bit
when we worked at Etsy together. And over the years we have talked extensively
about management and leadership. So I’ve had a certain idea of what I could
expect from her book. And the book absolutely delivered!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As a manager, one of your primary jobs is to foster a foundation of trust on your team</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the book Lara gives invaluable insights about the human side of management.
About the fact that as a manager you are tasked with making a group of humans
work together. And that only works if you understand what humans value, how
they tick, and if you’ve put the work in to build and foster a foundation of
trust on your team.</p>
<p>This common thread of understanding humans and using that to be effective at
work (and to be honest also outside) guides you through the whole book . Be it
mentoring, coaching, sponsoring, providing (and receiving) feedback, or
communication. Every chapter is written with humans in mind. And that is what
makes this such an outstanding book. Throughout the chapters you will learn how
to meet your team, grow your team, set expectations, communicate effectively,
and build resilience. Every chapter is to the point, clearly written, and
extremely actionable.</p>
<p>This book is a must have regardless whether you are a manager, want to become a
manager, reporting to a manager, or just in general work with other humans.
Lara Hogan puts down so much useful insights and wonderfully helpful guiding
questions and suggestions that I don’t think there is anyone who wouldn’t
benefit from reading it.  Plus it’s about 100 pages long. You can literally
start reading this book on Friday and will be better equipped to do your job on
Monday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Organized Mind: Thinking Straight in the Age of Information Overload</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-organized-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-organized-mind/</guid>
      <description>This book blew my mind (pun intended). There was so much neuropsychology in there that explained so many things about the brain.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book blew my mind (pun intended). There was so much neuropsychology in there that explained so many things about the brain. So many things I always wondered about made so much more sense now. I don’t know if it made me more organized but I have a whole new perspective on attention, memory, sleep, categorization, and so much more. This is one of those “game changer” books for me. I am approaching many things in daily life and even about my inner, emotional life very differently since reading the book. From how remembering and recalling things works (as far as we know currently), to how sleep impacts your brain, how categorization is done by humans (and why you will always end up with a “junk drawer”), and when to not trust your gut. It’s a book I want to read a second time because I don’t feel like I’ve fully taken it in yet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bullet Journal Method: Track the Past, Order the Present, Design the Future</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-bullet-journal-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-bullet-journal-method/</guid>
      <description>Very nice and easy read. Made me really think about slowing down for planning and reflection.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Very nice and easy read. Made me really think about slowing down for planning and reflection. I read this book after having switched to a Bullet Journal for daily logging and planning about 9 months prior. And it’s really easy to get sucked into all the pretty and elaborate spreads with bullet journaling and lose focus of what’s really important. The book does a really good job focusing on the fundamentals with bullet journaling and how to think about what to incorporate into your journaling practice.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maglev: Fast Software Load Balancer</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/maglev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/maglev/</guid>
      <description>Google&amp;rsquo;s network load balancer distributed system on commodity servers no physical deployment horizontally scalable load distribution via ECMP by network routers consistent hashing and connection tracking serving Google since 2008 Downside of hardware LB  limited vertical scale only 1+1 redundancy lack of flexibility + programmability expensive to upgrade     larger clusters have hardware encapsulators between maglev and router so they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be in the same L2 domain Linux kernel is circumvented for fast packet processing steering module consistent hashes between rx queues with packet rewrites threads rewrites checks for VIP match, connection table 5 tuple host over round robin for stability of connections (rr is fallback) 813 kpps for 1500 bytes IP packets processing speed of 9.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>Google&rsquo;s network load balancer</li>
<li>distributed system on commodity servers</li>
<li>no physical deployment</li>
<li>horizontally scalable</li>
<li>load distribution via ECMP by network routers</li>
<li>consistent hashing and connection tracking</li>
<li>serving Google since 2008</li>
<li>Downside of hardware LB
<ul>
<li>limited vertical scale</li>
<li>only 1+1 redundancy</li>
<li>lack of flexibility + programmability</li>
<li>expensive to upgrade</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/images/reading/maglev/sketch.png" alt="maglev architecture overview"></p>
<ul>
<li>larger clusters have hardware encapsulators between maglev and router so they don&rsquo;t need to be in the same L2 domain</li>
<li>Linux kernel is circumvented for fast packet processing</li>
<li>steering module consistent hashes between rx queues with packet rewrites threads</li>
<li>rewrites checks for VIP match, connection table</li>
<li>5 tuple host over round robin for stability of connections (rr is fallback)</li>
<li>813 kpps for 1500 bytes IP packets</li>
<li>processing speed of 9.06 Mpps for smaller packets</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="fast-packet-processing">Fast Packet Processing</h2>
<ul>
<li>userspace app circumventing kernel</li>
<li>shared packet pool with NIC</li>
<li>ring queue of pointers pointing to packets in pool</li>
<li>NIC and forwarder advance pointers in ring (no copying)</li>
<li>backend selection consistency across Maglev machines is accomplished by consistent hashing based on backend names (<strong>simplified algorithm!!</strong>)</li>
<li>kernel bypass 5x performance</li>
<li>handling fragments via special backend pool containing all Maglevs</li>
<li>special packet tracer packets that trigger Maglev to send debug info to SRC</li>
<li>steering module bottleneck before moving to 40Gbps</li>
<li>5 packet threads saturate 10Gbps NIC</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="questions">Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li><input disabled="" type="checkbox"> read up on ECMP</li>
<li><input disabled="" type="checkbox"> study Maglev hashing details</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Miracle Morning Journal</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-miracle-morning-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-miracle-morning-journal/</guid>
      <description>I wasn’t quite sure what to expect from this book. Morning routine inspiration always intrigues me.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wasn’t quite sure what to expect from this book. Morning routine inspiration always intrigues me. I’m a terrible early riser but I really enjoy being awake early. However the book was too much romanticism and extremes for me and not a lot I was taking away from reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Retrospective Handbook: A guide for agile teams</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-retrospective-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-retrospective-handbook/</guid>
      <description>This book provides a great overview of how to run good retrospectives and meetings in general.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book provides a great overview of how to run good retrospectives and meetings in general. While all the recommendations and tips on there are very apt and useful I&rsquo;ve found it a bit too practical and general. Most chapters are applicable to any form of meeting (which is good) but I would have loved a deeper dive into the psychological challenges and things to look out for with retrospectives.</p>
<p>At work we have a group of people which I&rsquo;m part of that work on making sure we have good frameworks in place for blameless postmortems and organizational learning as a whole. Part of that is moving past only investigating failure (via postmortems) and also look into investigating successes (via retrospectives). So in a similar way to how I&rsquo;ve spent time understanding the unhelpful concept of human error, I wanted to learn more about the theoretical concepts of successful retrospectives. Unfortunately this was completely the wrong book for this. It is a great and very practical read for retrospectives in the agile sense and how to run successful meetings in general. However I wasn&rsquo;t looking for that so I constantly kept thinking when we are going to dive into the meaty, theoretical stuff. This is in no way the authors fault
and I would highly recommend the book as inspiration for improving your meetings. But for the theoretical underpinnings of retrospectives as an organizational learning tool I&rsquo;m still on the lookout. Let me know if you have recommendations :).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective Monitoring and Alerting: For Web Operations</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/effective-monitoring-and-alerting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/effective-monitoring-and-alerting/</guid>
      <description>I was really looking forward to this book as I&amp;rsquo;ve heard good things about it and thought it would round up what I already knew about the topic.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was really looking forward to this book as I&rsquo;ve heard good things about it and thought it would round up what I already knew about the topic. However right from the start it felt rather awkward. The author is trying to maintain an abstract high level view on monitoring and alerting and not go into specific implementations. This makes for an awkward combination with it being basically a 101/introductory book on the topic. A lot of the formal descriptions of monitoring and alerting feel forced and don&rsquo;t hold up in the abstract very well and are too high level to be practical. He also talks about operations in an almost romantic hero style way which I didn&rsquo;t enjoy. In addition to that the book also includes some final chapters on outage handling and organizational and cultural setups. The terms human error, root cause analysis, and &ldquo;5 Whys&rdquo; are thrown around a lot with no acknowledgement of it being actually harmful to learning according to modern research in the field of systems safety. Definitely not a book I would recommend.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking in Systems: A Primer</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/thinking-in-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/thinking-in-systems/</guid>
      <description>This is a really great introduction to systems thinking. Meadows does a great job describing basic system properties, adding examples to illustrate them and then coming back to them later when describing related properties.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a really great introduction to systems thinking. Meadows does a great
job describing basic system properties, adding examples to illustrate them and
then coming back to them later when describing related properties. A lot of
the described things - especially at the beginning - almost seem like common
sense and suddenly you&rsquo;re neck deep in systems thinking. I especially liked
how she puts systems thinking into relation to being a mindful person. That
it&rsquo;s always a model and not the real world and that we still have to act as
morale humans. Highly recommended.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internet Of Garbage</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-internet-of-garbage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-internet-of-garbage/</guid>
      <description>In this book Sarah Jeong - a journalist trained as a lawyer at Harvard Law School - talks about the problem of online harassment.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this book Sarah Jeong - a journalist trained as a lawyer at Harvard Law School - talks about the problem of online harassment. It&rsquo;s another short but really good one. I&rsquo;ve learned a ton about copyright law and the limitations of current legislation when it comes to online harassment. But also things that
do work and what things could be attempted. It&rsquo;s a very sobering look at the current state of social networks, online harassment and tooling and legislation to help fight it. Definitely worth a read if you spend any time on the internet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dont-make-me-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dont-make-me-think/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m one of those engineers who used to happily claim to not have any frontend skills and just not be good at design.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m one of those engineers who used to happily claim to not have any frontend skills and just not be good at design. I came to loathe this thinking over the years and decided that if I can&rsquo;t do something I want to learn at least the basics. This is one of the reasons why I read &ldquo;Designing for Performance&rdquo; as mentioned above. Thankfully I also work with a ton of talented designers
and one of them is <a href="https://twitter.com/harllee">Jessica Harllee</a>. I talked to her about suggestions to get started with learning about design. And she said I should read &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t make me think&rdquo;. And she wasn&rsquo;t wrong. The book is a wonderful introduction into usability and design. The beauty of it is that while reading it, all of the things mentioned are total no-brainers. But you have to remember it while designing things. The other interesting thing for me was
that while all of the examples in the book are web based (with some brief stints into mobile) I could totally think of CLI apps I&rsquo;ve written in the past that totally do the wrong thing design-wise. Definitely a recommended read.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Men Explain Things to Me</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/men-explain-things-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/men-explain-things-to-me/</guid>
      <description>This collection of essays titled for the aggressive tendency of men to always have to explain things to women while assuming they have no idea what they are talking about.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This collection of essays titled for the aggressive tendency of men to always have to explain things to women while assuming they have no idea what they are talking about. The first essay brings this to a point by telling a story of a party where a man mansplains to the author the book she herself wrote. Without having actually read it. The book than continues with more essays that talk
about a lot more darker things like discussing domestic violence. The over arching theme is that the credibility of and respect towards women is continuously diminished to maintain the status quo and its power imbalance. Some of the essays towards the end of the book are not easy to read but it&rsquo;s more than worth it.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Credibility is a basic survival tool.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Mindfulness</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>This is another super short read and the de-facto introductory book to mindfulness meditation.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is another super short read and the de-facto introductory book to mindfulness meditation. There&rsquo;s not a lot to say here. It&rsquo;s good, give it a read as it&rsquo;s short enough to not matter if you end up not liking it. I started meditating regularly after reading it and it has been a great experience.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Boy Kings: A Journey into the Heart of the Social Network</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-boy-kings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-boy-kings/</guid>
      <description>The biography of Kate Losse about her time at (early stage) Facebook is in my mind a must read for any software engineer and especially if you&amp;rsquo;re a man.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The biography of Kate Losse about her time at (early stage) Facebook is in my mind a must read for any software engineer and especially if you&rsquo;re a man. It gives an extremely good insight view into what happens when young men are suddenly in charge of a ton of money. But more importantly it talks very bluntly about how engineers are treated differently from most other employees
for our supposed gift to turn any idea into gold with code.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Technology carries with it all the biases of the people who make it, so simply making the world more technical was not going to save us.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cybersexism: Sex, Gender and Power on the Internet</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/cybersexism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/cybersexism/</guid>
      <description>This short book by Laurie Penny is a very good read about sexism in the age of social networks and the omnipresent Internet.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This short book by Laurie Penny is a very good read about sexism in the age of social networks and the omnipresent Internet. It does a great job at talking about how a lot of familiar concepts of &ldquo;offline sexism&rdquo; are reinvented online and no news to women. It&rsquo;s short and insightful enough to recommend reading it
without hesitation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps one reason that women writers and technologists have, so far, the calmest and most comprehensive understanding of what surveillance technology really does to the human condition is that women grow up being watched.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/nonviolent-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/nonviolent-communication/</guid>
      <description>This has been recommended by many people I work with as a wonderful resource about positive human communication.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This has been recommended by many people I work with as a wonderful resource about positive human communication. And as - especially in a growing engineering org - communication is one of the most important skills to try to master, I decided to finally read this one. It&rsquo;s a very interesting book with an approach to communication that is rarely taught especially not to men. It
focuses on a collaborative rather than a competitive style of communication and the goal to reach agreements over winning arguments. The examples in the book are often pretty extreme coming from the author&rsquo;s work as a diplomat. And even though those are great to demonstrate how this way of communicating can work in the most extreme cases, it also shifts its focus a lot on explicit diplomatic style discussions. There are more examples that are more directed towards every day situations and even though the author is very explicit about this being useful in regular work meetings as well, I had a very hard time understanding how to practically apply those lessons in a meeting for example. That being said however it made me think a lot more about the way I
communicate and what I&rsquo;m saying versus what I want to say. I have also applied that way of communicating successfully at least once since reading the book. And I look forward to try it out more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Had Me at &#34;Hello, World&#34;: Mentoring Sessions with Industry Leaders at Microsoft, Facebook, Google, Amazon, Zynga and more!</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/you-had-me-at-hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/you-had-me-at-hello-world/</guid>
      <description>I found this book through Camille tweeting about the fact that she was also interviewed for it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found this book through <a href="https://twitter.com/skamille" title="@skamille on Twitter">Camille</a> tweeting about the fact that she was also interviewed for it. &ldquo;You had me at &lsquo;Hellow  World&rsquo;&rdquo; is a collection of interviews with industry leaders from successful companies about the many aspects of leadership and mentoring. It&rsquo;s a pretty lightweight read and a great resource to get some insight how successful people talk about those
topics. It does a great job in conveying how important skills outside of writing code are. And it provides good examples of how to use those for your advantage.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recoding Gender (History of Computing)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/recoding-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/recoding-gender/</guid>
      <description>I have a very complex relationship with the profession of &amp;ldquo;software engineering&amp;rdquo; and how it&amp;rsquo;s often defined in a non-inclusive way and as the profession of the golden children of society.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a very complex relationship with the profession of &ldquo;software engineering&rdquo; and how it&rsquo;s often defined in a non-inclusive way and as the profession of the golden children of society. Part of that is that I had always known a bit about the origins of programming and that a majority of programmers used to be women. But I didn&rsquo;t know a lot about it which is why I was excited to read this book. And it was great! The book walks you through the beginnings before and during WWII and what programming meant back then. It discusses how the emerging industry in this field changed job prospects and economic chances for women. But it also discusses how the image of a
programmer changed as more and more men participated. It&rsquo;s full of historical facts and documents and a more than wonderful read. It sparked a lot of thoughts for me and changed the way I think about my profession even more.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the traits that managers found most problematic in programmers were those
stereotypically associated with men</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Highly Sensitive Person in Love: Understanding and Managing Relationships When the World Overwhelms You</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-highly-sensitive-person-in-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-highly-sensitive-person-in-love/</guid>
      <description>I really liked the book. It was interesting to read about experiences of other highly sensitive people and to get a view from a psychologist on it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really liked the book. It was interesting to read about experiences of other highly sensitive people and to get a view from a psychologist on it. The book however has a way too touchy-feely style for me. And especially the final chapters talking about spirituality were a bit much for me. That being said I took a couple of things away from reading the book, I was more than once ready to throw the kindle across the room because my sensitivity got super hijacked by some things, and I&rsquo;m definitely better informed and at peace with my sensitivity than I was before.</p>
<p>I had no idea about the concept of highly sensitive people until I read <a href="http://m.huffpost.com/us/entry/4810794" title="Article about Highly Sensitive Person on Huffington Post">this article</a>. It has a pretty click-baity headline but it really hit home for me. So I decided to learn more about it and this book was the most prominent resource to pop up in my search. It&rsquo;s a really good book with a lot of great psychological insights and explicit case studies. At times
the way high sensitivity was described was a bit too feel-good for my taste. At other times I would almost throw my kindle across the room as the author managed to really sneak up on and hijack my sensitivity. The book focuses a lot on what usually goes wrong during childhood for highly sensitive people and makes it a point to relive memories and traumas through the lense of high sensitivity. This is a practice I really enjoyed although it felt a bit much to me at times as I consider my childhood to have been a happy one. On the other hand I started to do this practice with every day situations at work to help me understand why I feel what I feel in different situations. I identify myself as a highly sensitive person and the book was an extremely good read to
help me understand better what this could mean for me and my days.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leading Snowflakes</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/leading-snowflakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/leading-snowflakes/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed the book. It has a structure that is very easy to follow and definitely a quick read.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed the book. It has a structure that is very easy to follow and definitely a quick read. And even though I&rsquo;m not a manager or planning to become one, there&rsquo;s a lot of actionable advice in there for me as an engineer.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve heard about this book ever since it was released and a lot of people I know speak very highly of it. And they weren&rsquo;t wrong, I basically devoured the book in a weekend. It&rsquo;s very well written and has a ton of actionable advice for engineers becoming managers. But I would argue that this description
really limits the value of the book. I have no intention to become a manager at the moment however the book was really interesting and helpful for me. I think it&rsquo;s a great read for anyone looking to grow more into a leadership position.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manage Your Day-To-Day: Build Your Routine, Find Your Focus, and Sharpen Your Creative Mind</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/manage-your-day-to-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/manage-your-day-to-day/</guid>
      <description>This book sparked my interest while I was looking for improving my daily routines.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book sparked my interest while I was looking for improving my daily routines. I was often just starting the day as it happened often leaving me feel disorganized, unproductive, and imbalanced. Reading &ldquo;Manage your Day-to-Day&rdquo; gave me a lot of ideas of what things to try and add to my daily routine. And also to try and even have a daily routine. Something I picked up again through this book was journaling and while it has been on and off for the last couple of months I really enjoy it. The book was not mind blowing for me but I enjoyed reading it and definitely would recommend it if you are looking for inspiration for your daily routine.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It takes willpower to switch off the world, even for an hour.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing for Performance: Weighing Aesthetics and Speed</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/designing-for-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/designing-for-performance/</guid>
      <description>My coworker Laralara wrote this book last year and it was a lot of fun watching her process and how she knocked out that book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My coworker <a href="">Lara</a><a href="">lara</a> wrote this book last year and it was a lot of fun
watching her process and how she knocked out that book. Since then it was on
my list of books to read. Especially since I tend to shy away from frontend
things in my day job and want to get better at not doing that. The book is a
wonderful introduction into web performance especially from a design view. It
gives very solid technical details on a lot of things like browser rendering
and image formats that I only had very superficial knowledge of before. I
really enjoyed it and the book lead me to <a href="https://unwiredcouch.com/2015/07/24/frontend-performance.html">reduce the page weight of this blog
by 92%</a> which
was tons of fun to do as well.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The largest hurdle to creating and maintaining stellar site performance is
the culture of your organization.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feminism Is for Everybody: Passionate Politics</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/feminism-is-for-everybody/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/feminism-is-for-everybody/</guid>
      <description>I’ve known about this book for a while now, but up until early 2015 it was only available in print.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve known about this book for a while now, but up until early 2015 it was only available in print. And since I don’t really like owning physical books and read exclusively on my Kindle and iPhone I hadn’t bought it yet. So when I found out there is a Kindle version now, I immediately bought it. As expected, the book is really good and gives a good primer on feminism and the historical context from the author’s perspective. It reads less extreme to me as Greer which is very much in line with Hooks’ other writing. Definitely highly recommended for learning more about feminism.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Feminism is a movement to end sexism, sexist exploitation, and oppression.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Whole Woman</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-whole-woman/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-whole-woman/</guid>
      <description>I started reading this book in 2014 and finished it early 2015.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I started reading this book in 2014 and finished it early 2015. I overall liked it and it was really good in giving me different ways to think about feminism and how the whole system works together to enable sexism and exploitation. It&rsquo;s also a good resource to understand
better how closely related feminism and capitalism really are. However it comes with a really serious trigger warning. Germaine Greer is known to have very transphobic/cissexist views and this book is no exception. It is restricted to one chapter but those opinions - which I don&rsquo;t share at all - are definitely in there. So if this is a trigger for you, it&rsquo;s probably better to skip this book.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The pattern of devaluing women&rsquo;s contribution is as old as human
civilization</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Flow with OmniFocus</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/creating-flow-with-omnifocus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/creating-flow-with-omnifocus/</guid>
      <description>This one was kind of a surprise read for me. I’ve written before about how much I have OmniFocus is integrated in my life.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one was kind of a surprise read for me. I’ve written before about how much I have OmniFocus is integrated in my life. And when this book popped up in one of my RSS feeds I decided to give it a read. It’s definitely not a cheap book and I jumped over the first half as it’s basically an introduction into OmniFocus which I already know how to use. The book isn’t a total game changer, but the latter half gives some good food for thought on how to make the most of OmniFocus’ Perspectives and some unusual use cases for it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quiet: The Power of Introverts in a World That Can&#39;t Stop Talking</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/quiet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/quiet/</guid>
      <description>This is another one I started in 2013 and then dropped for no real reason.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is another one I started in 2013 and then dropped for no real reason. I finished it this year and thoroughly enjoyed it. I knew before I started reading that I fall on the introvert side of the scale but the book really helped recognizing some more patterns and making me feel better about it. This is also the only book I finished as a Kindle audiobook and while I likely won&rsquo;t do it again, it was an interesting experience. It&rsquo;s a great read and definitely recommended for anyone who works with other humans in their daily life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sketchnote Workbook: Advanced Techniques for Taking Visual Notes You Can Use Anywhere</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-sketchnote-workbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-sketchnote-workbook/</guid>
      <description>This was really fun to read. I didn’t end up picking up sketch noting as a permanent tool in note taking.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was really fun to read. I didn’t end up picking up sketch noting as a permanent tool in note taking. But I really enjoyed reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ETTO Principle: Efficiency-Thoroughness Trade-Off</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-etto-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-etto-principle/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s no secret that I&amp;rsquo;m interested in human factors and system safety and how to apply lessons learned to our field of creating and managing complex computer systems.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that I&rsquo;m interested in <a href="http://www.unwiredcouch.com/2014/08/04/human-error-getting-off-the-hook.html" title="Human Error and Getting Off The Hook on unwiredcouch.com">human factors and system safety</a> and how to apply lessons learned to our field of creating and managing complex computer systems. So it also shouldn&rsquo;t be a surprise that this book really hit home for me. It&rsquo;s well written and touches on a myriad of different aspects about how we trade off thoroughness for efficiency and how
production pressure changes our way of making decisions. It&rsquo;s a pretty fast read and I really enjoyed it. It also has a huge references and related literature section following each chapter which makes it great to start diving deeper into the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Phoenix Project: A Novel About IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-phoenix-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-phoenix-project/</guid>
      <description>I originally started reading it in 2013 when it came out and I enjoyed it back then.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I originally started reading it in 2013 when it came out and I enjoyed it back then. But I somehow still dropped the ball and stopped reading it. I finally went back and finished it this summer. It&rsquo;s a good and interesting read and having worked in traditional plant production companies I liked a lot of the parallels in there. It gets a little weird at the end and the last quarter feels like the authors really had to wrap up the book. And no matter how you
look at it, it&rsquo;s definitely business romanticism. But if you don&rsquo;t mind that, it&rsquo;s definitely entertaining.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing Chef: Getting the Most Out of Your Infrastructure Automation</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/customizing-chef/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/customizing-chef/</guid>
      <description>I added this as a bonus round, because while I definitely read it, I had the privilege to do so as a reviewer.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I added this as a bonus round, because while I definitely read it, I had the privilege to do so as a reviewer. I’m really happy that Jon asked me to review his book and while I had done a lot of Chef before, I learned tons about its internals from this book. If you work with Chef and want to get more out of it or even just understand some of the internals a little better, definitely read this book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Female Eunuch</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-female-eunuch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-female-eunuch/</guid>
      <description>I started the year off with finally finishing Germaine Greer&amp;rsquo;s feminist classic from 1970 about the role of women in modern society.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I started the year off with finally finishing Germaine Greer&rsquo;s feminist classic from 1970 about the role of women in modern society. I had known about the book for a couple of years and after having read “Bell Hooks' The Will to Change: Men, Masculinity, and Love” last year I decided to finally read
it. I definitely enjoyed it. Especially as a man it opens your eyes to a lot of things you never encounter in your daily life. It&rsquo;s very graphic at times and there are some long-winded parts in the middle but I would definitely recommend it to anyone who&rsquo;s interested in feminism. I also started reading her newest book &ldquo;The Whole Woman&rdquo; this year which is the sequel she never wanted to write. And so far I like it and it&rsquo;s alarming how few things have changed since &ldquo;The Female Eunuch&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field Guide to Understanding Human Error</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-field-guide-to-understanding-human-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-field-guide-to-understanding-human-error/</guid>
      <description>This is a must read book for anyone who’s interested in system resilience and human factors.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a must read book for anyone who’s interested in system resilience and human factors. I’d consider this the primer to get started and get a broad but not shallow entry into the world of human factors and resilience engineering.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Will to Change: Men, Masculinity, and Love</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-will-to-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-will-to-change/</guid>
      <description>I bought this book because I wanted to read up more on Feminism, structural sexism, toxic masculinity, and other related topics.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I bought this book because I wanted to read up more on Feminism, structural sexism, toxic masculinity, and other related topics. I’ve had many discussions about these before but never made the time to read actual books about it. I chose Bell Hooks as the first author to read on the topic as her name came up in many discussions about the topic. And I chose that book specifically to learn more about the role of men in all of this.</p>
<p>And the book was absolutely great. It does a great job of running through many areas where sexism and the patriarchy does a lot of harm to men as well. And it made me think a lot about my upbringing, childhood, and what kind of biases I carry because of it. But more importantly it made me think about the things that I value and was at times longing for. E.g. the fact that relationships between men are often very competitive and don’t provide any space for emotional depth and vulnerability. Limiting any chance of properly dealing with emotional situations in that setting.</p>
<p>I can wholeheartedly recommend this book to anyone (especially men) interested in learning more about the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Way to Go: A Thorough Introduction to the Go Programming Language</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-way-to-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-way-to-go/</guid>
      <description>This was a $3 Kindle purchase before I got on a flight.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was a $3 Kindle purchase before I got on a flight. And with the uptick in popularity of the Go programming language I thought it would be a good thing to learn about it. I don’t generally enjoy reading programming books but rather learn by trying to write some code. But this book did a good job of guiding me through the language and I felt pretty confident in diving in and giving it a try. Definitely more than worth the money.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Management for System Administrators: Stop Working Late and Start Working Smart</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/time-management-for-system-administrators/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/time-management-for-system-administrators/</guid>
      <description>I read this early on in my career switching to a job where I was occupied with running production services (as opposed to writing shipped software).</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read this early on in my career switching to a job where I was occupied with running production services (as opposed to writing shipped software). And I took a lot away from reading this book. Not only about time management but also an understanding of things that are common in the line of systems administration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test-Driven Infrastructure with Chef</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/test-driven-infrastructure-with-chef/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/test-driven-infrastructure-with-chef/</guid>
      <description>I wasn’t quite sure if I agree with using cucumber for integration testing of configuration management.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wasn’t quite sure if I agree with using cucumber for integration testing of configuration management. And after reading the book I still don’t. It’s hard to draw the line where you just test the implementation of the config management framework versus your own business logic. And I think it’s highly dependent on the level of advanced logic in your config management code. Although I definitely have seen code that would benefit from some testing like that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Riak Handbook</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-riak-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-riak-handbook/</guid>
      <description>I read this book some time in early 2012 shortly after moving to New York City.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read this book some time in early 2012 shortly after moving to New York
City. It was a staple on my Kindle while exploring the subway system, parks,
and coffee shops in a new city.</p>
<p><img src="/images/reading/the-riak-handbook/east-river.jpeg" alt=""></p>
<p>The Riak handbook is a great overview over one of the most popular and sophisticated NoSQL databases during the early 2010s. The book guides you through a number of easy to follow examples to learn all the basic properties of Riak. It uses JavaScript as an easy accessible language to understand the examples. It shows that Mathias has done deep research into the database and has put a lot of effort into creating an accessible resource to learn Riak.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
