<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Readings on unwiredcouch.com</title>
    <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Readings on unwiredcouch.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Outlining your Novel: Map Your Way to Success</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/outlining-your-novel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/outlining-your-novel/</guid>
      <description>I picked this book up because I’ve always been interested in outlining.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I picked this book up because I’ve always been interested in outlining. But even more so I’ve fascinated by how many people are fans of outlining. To the point where there are discussion about things like “is OmniOutliner or OneNote the better outlining app” and the point that there are even dedicated outlining apps. I’ve mostly done outlining for my writing with bullet points in a plain text or markdown file. And I wanted to know if I’m missing anything. In addition to that I also find the process of writing a book or novel super fascinating. I don’t know if I would want to write one. But the process of planning, structuring, and writing something of that size I find very interesting and fascinating. And I wanted to see if I could learn something from it for shorter writing like documentation and blog posts.</p>
<p>The book is structured in a way where only the first two chapters are really about outlining itself. The advantages of writing an outline versus writing “at the seat of your pants” as well as different approaches to outlines (e.g. mind maps, longform writing, bullet points) are discussed.</p>
<p>The following chapters then are a whirlwind tour through planning a novel and how to apply outlining to areas like plot planning, character development, or creating a backstory. At the end of every chapter there is an interview with a writer about the value and their approach in outlining.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed reading the book. I learned a lot about structuring my writing and what kind of things go into planning a novel. It’s very accessibly written and the chapters all have a good length so it never feels like they are dragged out or missing content. I could have done without the writer interviews as they didn’t really add a lot to the book but had a couple of interesting anecdotes. I don’t know if there would be anything new for a seasoned author in the book, but I can definitely recommend it as a quick intro into planning a novel.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1919</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/1919/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/1919/</guid>
      <description>I was interested in Eve Ewing’s writing ever since I read her run on Marvel’s Ironheart.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was interested in Eve Ewing’s writing ever since I read her run on Marvel’s Ironheart. So I got her other books a couple of months ago as well. I started with &ldquo;1919&rdquo; and it was definitely an interesting albeit completely new experience for me. I&rsquo;ve not really read poetry since school where I wasn&rsquo;t a big fan because it always felt forced. But while reading &ldquo;1919&rdquo; I definitely regretted not paying more attention in school to be able to pick up on the stylistic and technique choices in the book. &ldquo;1919&rdquo; is a collection of poems with the background of an official report about the 1919 race riots in Chicago which I had never heard of until I read the book. It was absolutely educational to read the various passages from the report that were the basis for the poem. And then get an emotional and very personal feeling poem about the passage right after. Given my own lack of knowledge about poetry I constantly felt like I was missing some fascinating nuances about the writing. And I&rsquo;ve started learning more about poetry and creative writing to rectify that. And I definitely plan to re-read &ldquo;1919&rdquo; once I&rsquo;m more knowledgeable about poetry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Draw People Every Day: Short Lessons in Portrait and Figure Drawing Using Ink and Color</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/draw-people-every-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/draw-people-every-day/</guid>
      <description>This book caught my eye while I was browsing for art books.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book caught my eye while I was browsing for art books. I’ve been trying
for a while to incorporate (almost) daily drawing back into my daily schedule.
But in a lighter weight way with less pressure to do finished pieces. And “Draw
People Every Day” definitely fit the bill for that. The book provides a great
high level overview for getting started with ink drawing and dives deeper into
various topics like e.g. the importance of drawing from life, gesture drawing
and how to achieve different effects with line weights. The same approach is
then taken in the final chapter to talk about using color for quick sketching.</p>
<p>After having spent a lot of time on learning how to draw in the last 2 years,
there weren’t a lot of things that were really new to me in this book. However
it’s the book I wish I had 2 years ago when I got started. It does a great job
laying down the fundamentals for getting started with sketching. And it
definitely inspired me to do more quick sketching and drawing from life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter and the Dinosaurs: The Astounding Interconnectedness of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dark-matter-and-the-dinosaurs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dark-matter-and-the-dinosaurs/</guid>
      <description>I had heard about this book on several occasions and when we went to the natural history museum here in Berlin I found it in the shop and decided to finally buy it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had heard about this book on several occasions and when we went to the natural history museum here in Berlin I found it in the shop and decided to finally buy it. I didn’t really know what to expect but having recently read a couple of popular science books (TODO: link to other reviews here) about physics I was very intrigued. And the book did definitely deliver, albeit in a very different way than I thought. I went into reading it with the expectation that the majority of the book would be about dark matter and its details. This however is really only a small part of the whole book. Throughout the book there are detailed explanations about the (presumed) origins of life, the makeup of the cosmos, mass extinctions, determining the age of rocks, history of scientific discoveries and methods, dinosaurs, impact crater anatomy, why Pluto isn’t a planet anymore, why meteroids as we call them often aren’t really meteroids, and much more. At the end of the book the author then circles back to dark matter and some of the recent theories and discoveries, tying all of the chapters together.</p>
<p>I have to admit that occasionally while reading the book I was fascinated by the things I was learning while at the same time not really knowing what it has to do with dark matter. Nevertheless I extremely enjoyed this book and the things I learned reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerate: Building and Scaling High-Performing Technology Organizations</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/accelerate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/accelerate/</guid>
      <description>This has come up in various discussions again and again so I finally decided to read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This has come up in various discussions again and again so I finally decided to read it. I didn’t really enjoy reading it much. It’s a good book and has a lot of good points. But also a couple I disagree with. But having worked so much in DevOps context, the book didn’t offer me anything new. More so some of it actually is opposite to my experience. Which made it even harder to continue reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sapiens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sapiens/</guid>
      <description>Usually I tend to shy away from longer (i.e. over 300 pages) books because I feel like I’m a somewhat slow reader.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Usually I tend to shy away from longer (i.e. over 300 pages) books because I
feel like I’m a somewhat slow reader. And it takes me too long to get through
and I feel demotivated to pick the book up. Sapiens still really piqued my
interest and it absolutely delivered.</p>
<p>The overall book is structured in chapters about the cognitive revolution, the
agricultural revolution, the unification of humankind, and the scientific
revolution. I’ve never thought about historical periods in that way and it was
interesting to see them presented in that way. The book covers the usual things
like evolution of Homo Sapiens with a bigger brain than other species, the
early periods as hunter gatherers, the emergence of agricultural and the
connected settling down.</p>
<p>The book also discusses cultural things like a common belief (e.g. religion or
capitalism) being a necessary establishment to allow for communication (and
collaboration to some extent) across larger territories than just family or
tribe boundaries. For any evolutionary step the trade-offs in those changes are
also discussed. Especially the cruel(-er) aspects of human dominance on the
planet.</p>
<p>I learned a lot reading this book and it definitely made me think about history
and human evolution from other perspectives than usual.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/drive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/drive/</guid>
      <description>I really liked especially the first part of the book that focuses on the science and research of motivation.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really liked especially the first part of the book that focuses on the
science and research of motivation. It was very interesting to read about the
history of behavioral psychology and how in various stages scientists ran
different experiments to understand the psychology of motivation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Wikipedia’s triumph seems to defy the laws of behavioral physics</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the more prominent examples of intrinsic motivation in the book is
contribution to open source. At that part it shows that the book was written
over 10 years ago. Because the discussion of open source is solely focused on
the positive effects of honing skills, furthering one’s career through the
work, and the intrinsic “feel good” motivation of giving back and contributing.
However over the last 10 years the problem of burn out with open source
maintainers has become a major topic that is completely absent here. And there
is also no real acknowledgement of maintainers vs contributors and the
difference in demand, work, and rewards. But I don’t think that detracts from
the points the book is making, merely something I immediately jumped to when
reading these packages as some missing nuance in the argument.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; rewards can perform a weird sort of behavioral alchemy: They can transform an interesting task into a drudge. They can turn play into work</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Large parts of the book then deal with the detrimental effects of the “carrot
and stick” approach to management. It was interesting to read about flow state,
rewards, and how - depending on how they are used - they can be actually
detrimental to motivation. This part contained an interesting short lesson in
management history and that the idea of creating space for autonomy for workers
has come up a couple of times in the past but never got a lot of traction. And
that the new way of granting autonomy and letting workers have more urgency
over their work is improving motivation. However there are also a couple of
dangerous ideas the author arrives at. That can easily be read as management
being a problem, rather than the fact that it is a craft that needs to honed
just as any other work</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps management is one of the forces that’s switching our default setting and <em>producing</em> that state [of passive inertia]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally there is a discussion about mastery and putting effort into something
that I found very interesting based on Carol Dweck’s - a psychology professor
at Stanford - research. The discussion of mastery being a mindset rather than a
set goal resonated a lot with me. Especially the idea that intelligence is not
a set entity within people but a resource that can be increased via learning.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That is the nature of mastery: Mastery is a mindset</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And finally the idea that mastery is an infinite pursuit. That even if you
spend a lifetime doing something, you can never truly master something. There
will always be more to learn, more to practice, more to &hellip; master.</p>
<p>Overall I really enjoyed the book. Even though there are definitely parts that
haven’t aged quite so well over the last 10 years and with all the things we’ve
learned from tech startups left and right misunderstanding the importance of
structure, management, and Human Resources. There were many parts that I really
enjoyed reading and learned a bunch of things from.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics and Philosophy: The Revolution in Modern Science</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/physics-and-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/physics-and-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>This book was just plain amazing. I didn’t know what to expect when I found this at the book store and I was reading books about (quantum) physics at the time, so I was curious to see that Heisenberg had written a book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book was just plain amazing. I didn’t know what to expect when I found this at the book store and I was reading books about (quantum) physics at the time, so I was curious to see that Heisenberg had written a book. A lot of the (quantum) physics details went over my head. But I loved the discussion of its implications on “reality” and the philosophy of being. It’s an extremely dense read but I got so much out of it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Aid for your Child&#39;s Mind: Simple steps to soothe anxiety, fears and worries</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/first-aid-for-your-childs-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/first-aid-for-your-childs-mind/</guid>
      <description>I also found this one by accident while looking through the book store.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I also found this one by accident while looking through the book store. It was interesting to read a psychologist’s view on dealing with anxiety in kids. And it turned out to be much more interesting and useful for its explanations of general behaving towards children. The exercises are a bit too involved for me to want to try them. But I can see them being useful.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weisse Nächte (Vollständige Deutsche Ausgabe)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/weisse-naechte/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/weisse-naechte/</guid>
      <description>I decided to give this book a try after poking around at the local book store.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I decided to give this book a try after poking around at the local book store. I realized I’ve never read a single Dostoyevsky. And I sure wasn’t gonna read “War &amp; Peace” just to give it a try and see how I like it. After some quick googling it seemed like “Weiße Nächte” was one of his fairly popular works, and they had it in the <a href="(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reclam">Reclam</a> version which is about 4 Euros. So not a huge investment.</p>
<p>So I read the whole thing with not a lot of expectations. And overall I didn’t hate it. It was slightly obnoxious at times, and Dostoyevsky seems to definitely have a thing for drama. Plus it has all the problems you can expect from a man during the 19th century when it comes to respecting women. The ending made up for a lot though.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Field Guide to Getting Lost</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-field-guide-to-getting-lost/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-field-guide-to-getting-lost/</guid>
      <description>This was another purchase while rummaging at the book store. I&amp;rsquo;ve read Solnit‘s „Men explain things to me“ a couple of years ago.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was another purchase while rummaging at the book  store. I&rsquo;ve read Solnit‘s „Men explain things to me“ a couple of years ago. And since I really enjoyed that one, I wanted to read another one of her works. I&rsquo;m not usually one for essays so it was definitely a different experience from reading more science related books.</p>
<p>I thoroughly enjoyed reading „A Field Guide to Getting Lost“ even though (or maybe because of?) I often found myself getting lost myself in an essay and wondering what&rsquo;s the point she&rsquo;s trying to be bring across. It was also at times deeply emotional to read for me as I was reminded of personal loss (or the fear of it) with many of her essays.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/digital-minimalism/</guid>
      <description>It took me quite a while after buying this book to find the excitement to actually read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It took me quite a while after buying this book to find the excitement to actually read it. Which had nothing to do with the book itself but the fact that I was already sold on the concept of &ldquo;Digital Minimalism&rdquo; and thought there wouldn’t be new or interesting things for me in there.</p>
<p>However once I started reading the book I immediately got sucked in and really enjoyed it. The book is very well researched and there are a lot of references to other works and research that are interesting to follow up on. It also contains a good mix of background information and actionable things to do for minimizing digital factors in once life. That makes it really easy (and somewhat also creates the desire to try) to give the exercises for minimization a spin.</p>
<p>My fear of already being sold on the concept and thus the book feeling like preaching to me as the choir were completely unfounded. If anything I got a confirmation and reaffirmation to my own practices of minimizing digital influences on my life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Logic in an Illogical World</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-logic/</guid>
      <description>This book gives a thorough introduction into logic and how to apply it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book gives a thorough introduction into logic and how to apply it. And I really enjoyed the discussion of what kind of things can be applied, how to build a logical structure and argument, and what the limits of a logical argument are.</p>
<p>I especially enjoyed the discussions of axioms as a kind of personal value system. And thus the root of any logical reasoning that you apply to arguments. This was the part for me that really tied the theoretical approach of logic and the emotional and moral foundations of one’s own beliefs together.</p>
<p>Overall however I wanted this book to be better. While I really enjoyed the logic part, there was one thing that made it really hard for me to get into a flow while reading. The author kept jumping between theory and examples way too frequently for my taste. She also rarely used lighter &ldquo;introductory&rdquo; examples. But most of the time jumped straight into heavy examples around racism, sexism, and other topics like that. Which made it much harder for me to get an understanding of the logical foundations as I was trying to keep the theoretical ideas in my head while also dealing with the emotional reaction to such heavy examples. I don’t think that those didn’t have a part in the book at all, but rather for me it would have worked better to reserve these heavy examples for the end. At which point I had familiarized myself with the concepts that got introduced, had some simple examples to apply them, and could focus on a more trying example as a completion of the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Watercolor Artist&#39;s Bible</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-watercolor-bible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-watercolor-bible/</guid>
      <description>A while into learning how to draw I realized that watercolor is a lot more fun and versatile than I thought it was from my experience using it in art class in school.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A while into learning how to draw I realized that watercolor is a lot more fun and versatile than I thought it was from my experience using it in art class in school. So I researched around and found this book recommended as a sort of reference book for watercolor artists. And it’s exactly that. The book gives a great overview over all the different aspects and techniques of using watercolor. Reading it gave me a much better understanding of the medium and I still refer back to it to look some things up occasionally.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Briefer History of Time</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-briefer-history-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/a-briefer-history-of-time/</guid>
      <description>I decided to read this new edition of “A Brief History of Time”, which I had started but never finished.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I decided to read this new edition of “A Brief History of Time”, which I had started but never finished. I really enjoyed it even though most of it went totally over my head. I read this book on the Kindle and mostly before going to sleep. Which is not a good combination for reading a book with such an intense topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sketch Every Day: 100&#43; simple drawing exercises from Simone Grünewald</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sketch-every-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/sketch-every-day/</guid>
      <description>I absolutely loved this book. It was more of a flip through and reading individual chapters for me than a book I read front to back.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I absolutely loved this book. It was more of a flip through and reading individual chapters for me than a book I read front to back. The chapters cover the author’s creative journey, some general advice for artists, art fundamentals, character design, and even a chapter on managing a family life while also making time and space for art. Every chapter and its sub sections contain a ton of very helpful examples. All drawn in Simone Grünewald’s well known style. So it’s easy to see how to approach faces, noses, hair, old and young people. And even flora and fauna.</p>
<p>The whole book is absolutely fun to read and I can highly recommend it for learning and inspiration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee Nerd: How to Have Your Coffee and Drink It Too</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/coffee-nerd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/coffee-nerd/</guid>
      <description>Really enjoyed the book. I’ve been nerding out on coffee for a couple of years now and I’ve definitely learned a bunch of new things through the book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Really enjoyed the book. I’ve been nerding out on coffee for a couple of years now and I’ve definitely learned a bunch of new things through the book. And it’s absolutely entertainingly written. Definitely recommended if you’re into coffee.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calm Technology: Designing for Billions of Devices and the Internet of Things</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/calm-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/calm-technology/</guid>
      <description>I was pretty excited about this book. I used to follow Amber Case on social media and she did some interesting early IoT stuff.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was pretty excited about this book. I used to follow Amber Case on social media and she did some interesting early IoT stuff. But the book overall is written with mostly anecdotal examples and not many directly practical things. It also has some confusing layout quirks that occasionally makes it hard to read. But content wise it&rsquo;s pretty good if you’re new to the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tree of Yoga</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-tree-of-yoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-tree-of-yoga/</guid>
      <description>I didn’t much enjoy the book which might be due to expecting something different.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn’t much enjoy the book which might be due to expecting something different. I didn’t have strong expectation but I wanted to get some more background on where yoga is coming from and what else is part of it to enhance my own yoga (and maybe meditation) practice. And I’ve definitely learned a couple of things from the book. But those could have been summarized on 10 pages. The rest of the time I’ve felt the book to mostly be repetitive, rambling, almost condescending at times, and even occasionally dangerously wrong (e.g. there’s a section in which it’s said that inverted poses while menstruating can lead to cancer).</p>
<p>There are definitely good things in there about balance, not seeing yoga practice as a competition, listening to your body, taking time, etc. But as a fairly scientific person it’s hard to read over the parts where the last 100 years of modern medicine are ignored.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slack: Getting Past Burnout, Busywork, and the Myth of Total Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/slack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/slack/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed this book. As someone who has not been actively part of the dotcom era, and has mostly been told about the bad sides of that time, it’s refreshing to read something coming out of that time full of what are still essentially progressive ideas today.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed this book. As someone who has not been actively part of the dotcom era, and has mostly been told about the bad sides of that time, it’s refreshing to read something coming out of that time full of what are still essentially progressive ideas today. Slack as the part of the work where innovation happens vs the always on, always busy culture is something organizations can still learn heaps from today. Definitely recommend reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Oneself (Harvard Business Review Classics)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/managing-oneself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/managing-oneself/</guid>
      <description>It’s really short, more of an essay really, so there’s no reason not to read it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s really short, more of an essay really, so there’s no reason not to read it. It gives a couple of really good and fairly practical tips about what to find out about oneself in order to be effective and successful.</p>
<p>One of the things that definitely did strike me as interesting were Drucker’s points about taking notes and writing things down in general:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If I don’t write it down immediately, I forget it right away. If I put it into a sketch book, I never forget it and I never have to look it up again</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve had this experience so frequently, especially as a kid in school. That when I wrote something down (e.g. homework for the day) I rarely needed to look it up again but remembered what I had to do. Because I would also often remember it either way, I sadly drew the wrong conclusion there (namely that writing things down isn’t worth the hassle). Which stifled my note taking skills and a lot of my learning later on. It wasn’t until a couple of years ago that I realized that it was precisely that process of writing things down that made me memorize my homework.</p>
<p>A good part of the book also is about figuring out which version of yourself you want to be. Which I think is a really important aspect of maturing as a person and figuring out why you’re even trying to get better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That is the mirror test. Ethics requires that you ask yourself, what kind of person do I want to see in the mirror in the morning?</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technically Wrong: Sexist Apps, Biased Algorithms, and Other Threats of Toxic Tech</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/technically-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/technically-wrong/</guid>
      <description>This is a fantastic book. It walks through many different facets of how interfaces are causing people to have a hard time instead of being useful.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a fantastic book. It walks through many different facets of how interfaces are causing people to have a hard time instead of being useful. And looks at many different factors contributing to the status quo. I’ve definitely spent a lot of time educating myself on the topic before and while some things I already knew about, the book provided a great mix of new information, different view points, and reminders for myself. I wholeheartedly recommend this to anyone working in tech.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resilient Management</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/resilient-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/resilient-management/</guid>
      <description>I’ve known Lara for years and have also been part of her organization for a bit when we worked at Etsy together.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve known Lara for years and have also been part of her organization for a bit
when we worked at Etsy together. And over the years we have talked extensively
about management and leadership. So I’ve had a certain idea of what I could
expect from her book. And the book absolutely delivered!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As a manager, one of your primary jobs is to foster a foundation of trust on your team</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the book Lara gives invaluable insights about the human side of management.
About the fact that as a manager you are tasked with making a group of humans
work together. And that only works if you understand what humans value, how
they tick, and if you’ve put the work in to build and foster a foundation of
trust on your team.</p>
<p>This common thread of understanding humans and using that to be effective at
work (and to be honest also outside) guides you through the whole book . Be it
mentoring, coaching, sponsoring, providing (and receiving) feedback, or
communication. Every chapter is written with humans in mind. And that is what
makes this such an outstanding book. Throughout the chapters you will learn how
to meet your team, grow your team, set expectations, communicate effectively,
and build resilience. Every chapter is to the point, clearly written, and
extremely actionable.</p>
<p>This book is a must have regardless whether you are a manager, want to become a
manager, reporting to a manager, or just in general work with other humans.
Lara Hogan puts down so much useful insights and wonderfully helpful guiding
questions and suggestions that I don’t think there is anyone who wouldn’t
benefit from reading it.  Plus it’s about 100 pages long. You can literally
start reading this book on Friday and will be better equipped to do your job on
Monday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Retrospective Handbook: A guide for agile teams</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-retrospective-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-retrospective-handbook/</guid>
      <description>This book provides a great overview of how to run good retrospectives and meetings in general.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book provides a great overview of how to run good retrospectives and meetings in general. While all the recommendations and tips on there are very apt and useful I&rsquo;ve found it a bit too practical and general. Most chapters are applicable to any form of meeting (which is good) but I would have loved a deeper dive into the psychological challenges and things to look out for with retrospectives.</p>
<p>At work we have a group of people which I&rsquo;m part of that work on making sure we have good frameworks in place for blameless postmortems and organizational learning as a whole. Part of that is moving past only investigating failure (via postmortems) and also look into investigating successes (via retrospectives). So in a similar way to how I&rsquo;ve spent time understanding the unhelpful concept of human error, I wanted to learn more about the theoretical concepts of successful retrospectives. Unfortunately this was completely the wrong book for this. It is a great and very practical read for retrospectives in the agile sense and how to run successful meetings in general. However I wasn&rsquo;t looking for that so I constantly kept thinking when we are going to dive into the meaty, theoretical stuff. This is in no way the authors fault
and I would highly recommend the book as inspiration for improving your meetings. But for the theoretical underpinnings of retrospectives as an organizational learning tool I&rsquo;m still on the lookout. Let me know if you have recommendations :).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective Monitoring and Alerting: For Web Operations</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/effective-monitoring-and-alerting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/effective-monitoring-and-alerting/</guid>
      <description>I was really looking forward to this book as I&amp;rsquo;ve heard good things about it and thought it would round up what I already knew about the topic.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was really looking forward to this book as I&rsquo;ve heard good things about it and thought it would round up what I already knew about the topic. However right from the start it felt rather awkward. The author is trying to maintain an abstract high level view on monitoring and alerting and not go into specific implementations. This makes for an awkward combination with it being basically a 101/introductory book on the topic. A lot of the formal descriptions of monitoring and alerting feel forced and don&rsquo;t hold up in the abstract very well and are too high level to be practical. He also talks about operations in an almost romantic hero style way which I didn&rsquo;t enjoy. In addition to that the book also includes some final chapters on outage handling and organizational and cultural setups. The terms human error, root cause analysis, and &ldquo;5 Whys&rdquo; are thrown around a lot with no acknowledgement of it being actually harmful to learning according to modern research in the field of systems safety. Definitely not a book I would recommend.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internet Of Garbage</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-internet-of-garbage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-internet-of-garbage/</guid>
      <description>In this book Sarah Jeong - a journalist trained as a lawyer at Harvard Law School - talks about the problem of online harassment.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this book Sarah Jeong - a journalist trained as a lawyer at Harvard Law School - talks about the problem of online harassment. It&rsquo;s another short but really good one. I&rsquo;ve learned a ton about copyright law and the limitations of current legislation when it comes to online harassment. But also things that
do work and what things could be attempted. It&rsquo;s a very sobering look at the current state of social networks, online harassment and tooling and legislation to help fight it. Definitely worth a read if you spend any time on the internet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dont-make-me-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/dont-make-me-think/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m one of those engineers who used to happily claim to not have any frontend skills and just not be good at design.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m one of those engineers who used to happily claim to not have any frontend skills and just not be good at design. I came to loathe this thinking over the years and decided that if I can&rsquo;t do something I want to learn at least the basics. This is one of the reasons why I read &ldquo;Designing for Performance&rdquo; as mentioned above. Thankfully I also work with a ton of talented designers
and one of them is <a href="https://twitter.com/harllee">Jessica Harllee</a>. I talked to her about suggestions to get started with learning about design. And she said I should read &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t make me think&rdquo;. And she wasn&rsquo;t wrong. The book is a wonderful introduction into usability and design. The beauty of it is that while reading it, all of the things mentioned are total no-brainers. But you have to remember it while designing things. The other interesting thing for me was
that while all of the examples in the book are web based (with some brief stints into mobile) I could totally think of CLI apps I&rsquo;ve written in the past that totally do the wrong thing design-wise. Definitely a recommended read.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Men Explain Things to Me</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/men-explain-things-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/men-explain-things-to-me/</guid>
      <description>This collection of essays titled for the aggressive tendency of men to always have to explain things to women while assuming they have no idea what they are talking about.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This collection of essays titled for the aggressive tendency of men to always have to explain things to women while assuming they have no idea what they are talking about. The first essay brings this to a point by telling a story of a party where a man mansplains to the author the book she herself wrote. Without having actually read it. The book than continues with more essays that talk
about a lot more darker things like discussing domestic violence. The over arching theme is that the credibility of and respect towards women is continuously diminished to maintain the status quo and its power imbalance. Some of the essays towards the end of the book are not easy to read but it&rsquo;s more than worth it.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Credibility is a basic survival tool.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Mindfulness</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-art-of-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>This is another super short read and the de-facto introductory book to mindfulness meditation.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is another super short read and the de-facto introductory book to mindfulness meditation. There&rsquo;s not a lot to say here. It&rsquo;s good, give it a read as it&rsquo;s short enough to not matter if you end up not liking it. I started meditating regularly after reading it and it has been a great experience.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Boy Kings: A Journey into the Heart of the Social Network</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-boy-kings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-boy-kings/</guid>
      <description>The biography of Kate Losse about her time at (early stage) Facebook is in my mind a must read for any software engineer and especially if you&amp;rsquo;re a man.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The biography of Kate Losse about her time at (early stage) Facebook is in my mind a must read for any software engineer and especially if you&rsquo;re a man. It gives an extremely good insight view into what happens when young men are suddenly in charge of a ton of money. But more importantly it talks very bluntly about how engineers are treated differently from most other employees
for our supposed gift to turn any idea into gold with code.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Technology carries with it all the biases of the people who make it, so simply making the world more technical was not going to save us.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cybersexism: Sex, Gender and Power on the Internet</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/cybersexism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/cybersexism/</guid>
      <description>This short book by Laurie Penny is a very good read about sexism in the age of social networks and the omnipresent Internet.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This short book by Laurie Penny is a very good read about sexism in the age of social networks and the omnipresent Internet. It does a great job at talking about how a lot of familiar concepts of &ldquo;offline sexism&rdquo; are reinvented online and no news to women. It&rsquo;s short and insightful enough to recommend reading it
without hesitation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps one reason that women writers and technologists have, so far, the calmest and most comprehensive understanding of what surveillance technology really does to the human condition is that women grow up being watched.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/nonviolent-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/nonviolent-communication/</guid>
      <description>This has been recommended by many people I work with as a wonderful resource about positive human communication.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This has been recommended by many people I work with as a wonderful resource about positive human communication. And as - especially in a growing engineering org - communication is one of the most important skills to try to master, I decided to finally read this one. It&rsquo;s a very interesting book with an approach to communication that is rarely taught especially not to men. It
focuses on a collaborative rather than a competitive style of communication and the goal to reach agreements over winning arguments. The examples in the book are often pretty extreme coming from the author&rsquo;s work as a diplomat. And even though those are great to demonstrate how this way of communicating can work in the most extreme cases, it also shifts its focus a lot on explicit diplomatic style discussions. There are more examples that are more directed towards every day situations and even though the author is very explicit about this being useful in regular work meetings as well, I had a very hard time understanding how to practically apply those lessons in a meeting for example. That being said however it made me think a lot more about the way I
communicate and what I&rsquo;m saying versus what I want to say. I have also applied that way of communicating successfully at least once since reading the book. And I look forward to try it out more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Had Me at &#34;Hello, World&#34;: Mentoring Sessions with Industry Leaders at Microsoft, Facebook, Google, Amazon, Zynga and more!</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/you-had-me-at-hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/you-had-me-at-hello-world/</guid>
      <description>I found this book through Camille tweeting about the fact that she was also interviewed for it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found this book through <a href="https://twitter.com/skamille" title="@skamille on Twitter">Camille</a> tweeting about the fact that she was also interviewed for it. &ldquo;You had me at &lsquo;Hellow  World&rsquo;&rdquo; is a collection of interviews with industry leaders from successful companies about the many aspects of leadership and mentoring. It&rsquo;s a pretty lightweight read and a great resource to get some insight how successful people talk about those
topics. It does a great job in conveying how important skills outside of writing code are. And it provides good examples of how to use those for your advantage.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recoding Gender (History of Computing)</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/recoding-gender/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/recoding-gender/</guid>
      <description>I have a very complex relationship with the profession of &amp;ldquo;software engineering&amp;rdquo; and how it&amp;rsquo;s often defined in a non-inclusive way and as the profession of the golden children of society.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a very complex relationship with the profession of &ldquo;software engineering&rdquo; and how it&rsquo;s often defined in a non-inclusive way and as the profession of the golden children of society. Part of that is that I had always known a bit about the origins of programming and that a majority of programmers used to be women. But I didn&rsquo;t know a lot about it which is why I was excited to read this book. And it was great! The book walks you through the beginnings before and during WWII and what programming meant back then. It discusses how the emerging industry in this field changed job prospects and economic chances for women. But it also discusses how the image of a
programmer changed as more and more men participated. It&rsquo;s full of historical facts and documents and a more than wonderful read. It sparked a lot of thoughts for me and changed the way I think about my profession even more.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the traits that managers found most problematic in programmers were those
stereotypically associated with men</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Highly Sensitive Person in Love: Understanding and Managing Relationships When the World Overwhelms You</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-highly-sensitive-person-in-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-highly-sensitive-person-in-love/</guid>
      <description>I really liked the book. It was interesting to read about experiences of other highly sensitive people and to get a view from a psychologist on it.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really liked the book. It was interesting to read about experiences of other highly sensitive people and to get a view from a psychologist on it. The book however has a way too touchy-feely style for me. And especially the final chapters talking about spirituality were a bit much for me. That being said I took a couple of things away from reading the book, I was more than once ready to throw the kindle across the room because my sensitivity got super hijacked by some things, and I&rsquo;m definitely better informed and at peace with my sensitivity than I was before.</p>
<p>I had no idea about the concept of highly sensitive people until I read <a href="http://m.huffpost.com/us/entry/4810794" title="Article about Highly Sensitive Person on Huffington Post">this article</a>. It has a pretty click-baity headline but it really hit home for me. So I decided to learn more about it and this book was the most prominent resource to pop up in my search. It&rsquo;s a really good book with a lot of great psychological insights and explicit case studies. At times
the way high sensitivity was described was a bit too feel-good for my taste. At other times I would almost throw my kindle across the room as the author managed to really sneak up on and hijack my sensitivity. The book focuses a lot on what usually goes wrong during childhood for highly sensitive people and makes it a point to relive memories and traumas through the lense of high sensitivity. This is a practice I really enjoyed although it felt a bit much to me at times as I consider my childhood to have been a happy one. On the other hand I started to do this practice with every day situations at work to help me understand why I feel what I feel in different situations. I identify myself as a highly sensitive person and the book was an extremely good read to
help me understand better what this could mean for me and my days.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leading Snowflakes</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/leading-snowflakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/leading-snowflakes/</guid>
      <description>I really enjoyed the book. It has a structure that is very easy to follow and definitely a quick read.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed the book. It has a structure that is very easy to follow and definitely a quick read. And even though I&rsquo;m not a manager or planning to become one, there&rsquo;s a lot of actionable advice in there for me as an engineer.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve heard about this book ever since it was released and a lot of people I know speak very highly of it. And they weren&rsquo;t wrong, I basically devoured the book in a weekend. It&rsquo;s very well written and has a ton of actionable advice for engineers becoming managers. But I would argue that this description
really limits the value of the book. I have no intention to become a manager at the moment however the book was really interesting and helpful for me. I think it&rsquo;s a great read for anyone looking to grow more into a leadership position.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manage Your Day-To-Day: Build Your Routine, Find Your Focus, and Sharpen Your Creative Mind</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/manage-your-day-to-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/manage-your-day-to-day/</guid>
      <description>This book sparked my interest while I was looking for improving my daily routines.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book sparked my interest while I was looking for improving my daily routines. I was often just starting the day as it happened often leaving me feel disorganized, unproductive, and imbalanced. Reading &ldquo;Manage your Day-to-Day&rdquo; gave me a lot of ideas of what things to try and add to my daily routine. And also to try and even have a daily routine. Something I picked up again through this book was journaling and while it has been on and off for the last couple of months I really enjoy it. The book was not mind blowing for me but I enjoyed reading it and definitely would recommend it if you are looking for inspiration for your daily routine.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It takes willpower to switch off the world, even for an hour.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing for Performance: Weighing Aesthetics and Speed</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/designing-for-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/designing-for-performance/</guid>
      <description>My coworker Laralara wrote this book last year and it was a lot of fun watching her process and how she knocked out that book.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My coworker <a href="">Lara</a><a href="">lara</a> wrote this book last year and it was a lot of fun
watching her process and how she knocked out that book. Since then it was on
my list of books to read. Especially since I tend to shy away from frontend
things in my day job and want to get better at not doing that. The book is a
wonderful introduction into web performance especially from a design view. It
gives very solid technical details on a lot of things like browser rendering
and image formats that I only had very superficial knowledge of before. I
really enjoyed it and the book lead me to <a href="https://unwiredcouch.com/2015/07/24/frontend-performance.html">reduce the page weight of this blog
by 92%</a> which
was tons of fun to do as well.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The largest hurdle to creating and maintaining stellar site performance is
the culture of your organization.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feminism Is for Everybody: Passionate Politics</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/feminism-is-for-everybody/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/feminism-is-for-everybody/</guid>
      <description>I’ve known about this book for a while now, but up until early 2015 it was only available in print.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve known about this book for a while now, but up until early 2015 it was only available in print. And since I don’t really like owning physical books and read exclusively on my Kindle and iPhone I hadn’t bought it yet. So when I found out there is a Kindle version now, I immediately bought it. As expected, the book is really good and gives a good primer on feminism and the historical context from the author’s perspective. It reads less extreme to me as Greer which is very much in line with Hooks’ other writing. Definitely highly recommended for learning more about feminism.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Feminism is a movement to end sexism, sexist exploitation, and oppression.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Whole Woman</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-whole-woman/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-whole-woman/</guid>
      <description>I started reading this book in 2014 and finished it early 2015.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I started reading this book in 2014 and finished it early 2015. I overall liked it and it was really good in giving me different ways to think about feminism and how the whole system works together to enable sexism and exploitation. It&rsquo;s also a good resource to understand
better how closely related feminism and capitalism really are. However it comes with a really serious trigger warning. Germaine Greer is known to have very transphobic/cissexist views and this book is no exception. It is restricted to one chapter but those opinions - which I don&rsquo;t share at all - are definitely in there. So if this is a trigger for you, it&rsquo;s probably better to skip this book.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The pattern of devaluing women&rsquo;s contribution is as old as human
civilization</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Flow with OmniFocus</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/creating-flow-with-omnifocus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/creating-flow-with-omnifocus/</guid>
      <description>This one was kind of a surprise read for me. I’ve written before about how much I have OmniFocus is integrated in my life.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one was kind of a surprise read for me. I’ve written before about how much I have OmniFocus is integrated in my life. And when this book popped up in one of my RSS feeds I decided to give it a read. It’s definitely not a cheap book and I jumped over the first half as it’s basically an introduction into OmniFocus which I already know how to use. The book isn’t a total game changer, but the latter half gives some good food for thought on how to make the most of OmniFocus’ Perspectives and some unusual use cases for it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quiet: The Power of Introverts in a World That Can&#39;t Stop Talking</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/quiet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/quiet/</guid>
      <description>This is another one I started in 2013 and then dropped for no real reason.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is another one I started in 2013 and then dropped for no real reason. I finished it this year and thoroughly enjoyed it. I knew before I started reading that I fall on the introvert side of the scale but the book really helped recognizing some more patterns and making me feel better about it. This is also the only book I finished as a Kindle audiobook and while I likely won&rsquo;t do it again, it was an interesting experience. It&rsquo;s a great read and definitely recommended for anyone who works with other humans in their daily life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ETTO Principle: Efficiency-Thoroughness Trade-Off</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-etto-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-etto-principle/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s no secret that I&amp;rsquo;m interested in human factors and system safety and how to apply lessons learned to our field of creating and managing complex computer systems.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that I&rsquo;m interested in <a href="http://www.unwiredcouch.com/2014/08/04/human-error-getting-off-the-hook.html" title="Human Error and Getting Off The Hook on unwiredcouch.com">human factors and system safety</a> and how to apply lessons learned to our field of creating and managing complex computer systems. So it also shouldn&rsquo;t be a surprise that this book really hit home for me. It&rsquo;s well written and touches on a myriad of different aspects about how we trade off thoroughness for efficiency and how
production pressure changes our way of making decisions. It&rsquo;s a pretty fast read and I really enjoyed it. It also has a huge references and related literature section following each chapter which makes it great to start diving deeper into the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Phoenix Project: A Novel About IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-phoenix-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-phoenix-project/</guid>
      <description>I originally started reading it in 2013 when it came out and I enjoyed it back then.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I originally started reading it in 2013 when it came out and I enjoyed it back then. But I somehow still dropped the ball and stopped reading it. I finally went back and finished it this summer. It&rsquo;s a good and interesting read and having worked in traditional plant production companies I liked a lot of the parallels in there. It gets a little weird at the end and the last quarter feels like the authors really had to wrap up the book. And no matter how you
look at it, it&rsquo;s definitely business romanticism. But if you don&rsquo;t mind that, it&rsquo;s definitely entertaining.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing Chef: Getting the Most Out of Your Infrastructure Automation</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/customizing-chef/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/customizing-chef/</guid>
      <description>I added this as a bonus round, because while I definitely read it, I had the privilege to do so as a reviewer.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I added this as a bonus round, because while I definitely read it, I had the privilege to do so as a reviewer. I’m really happy that Jon asked me to review his book and while I had done a lot of Chef before, I learned tons about its internals from this book. If you work with Chef and want to get more out of it or even just understand some of the internals a little better, definitely read this book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Female Eunuch</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-female-eunuch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-female-eunuch/</guid>
      <description>I started the year off with finally finishing Germaine Greer&amp;rsquo;s feminist classic from 1970 about the role of women in modern society.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I started the year off with finally finishing Germaine Greer&rsquo;s feminist classic from 1970 about the role of women in modern society. I had known about the book for a couple of years and after having read “Bell Hooks&rsquo; The Will to Change: Men, Masculinity, and Love” last year I decided to finally read
it. I definitely enjoyed it. Especially as a man it opens your eyes to a lot of things you never encounter in your daily life. It&rsquo;s very graphic at times and there are some long-winded parts in the middle but I would definitely recommend it to anyone who&rsquo;s interested in feminism. I also started reading her newest book &ldquo;The Whole Woman&rdquo; this year which is the sequel she never wanted to write. And so far I like it and it&rsquo;s alarming how few things have changed since &ldquo;The Female Eunuch&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Will to Change: Men, Masculinity, and Love</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-will-to-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-will-to-change/</guid>
      <description>I bought this book because I wanted to read up more on Feminism, structural sexism, toxic masculinity, and other related topics.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I bought this book because I wanted to read up more on Feminism, structural sexism, toxic masculinity, and other related topics. I’ve had many discussions about these before but never made the time to read actual books about it. I chose Bell Hooks as the first author to read on the topic as her name came up in many discussions about the topic. And I chose that book specifically to learn more about the role of men in all of this.</p>
<p>And the book was absolutely great. It does a great job of running through many areas where sexism and the patriarchy does a lot of harm to men as well. And it made me think a lot about my upbringing, childhood, and what kind of biases I carry because of it. But more importantly it made me think about the things that I value and was at times longing for. E.g. the fact that relationships between men are often very competitive and don’t provide any space for emotional depth and vulnerability. Limiting any chance of properly dealing with emotional situations in that setting.</p>
<p>I can wholeheartedly recommend this book to anyone (especially men) interested in learning more about the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Way to Go: A Thorough Introduction to the Go Programming Language</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-way-to-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-way-to-go/</guid>
      <description>This was a $3 Kindle purchase before I got on a flight.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was a $3 Kindle purchase before I got on a flight. And with the uptick in popularity of the Go programming language I thought it would be a good thing to learn about it. I don’t generally enjoy reading programming books but rather learn by trying to write some code. But this book did a good job of guiding me through the language and I felt pretty confident in diving in and giving it a try. Definitely more than worth the money.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Riak Handbook</title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-riak-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>d@unwiredcouch.com (Daniel Schauenberg)</author>
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/reading/the-riak-handbook/</guid>
      <description>I read this book some time in early 2012 shortly after moving to New York City.</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read this book some time in early 2012 shortly after moving to New York
City. It was a staple on my Kindle while exploring the subway system, parks,
and coffee shops in a new city.</p>
<p><img src="/images/reading/the-riak-handbook/east-river.jpeg" alt=""></p>
<p>The Riak handbook is a great overview over one of the most popular and sophisticated NoSQL databases during the early 2010s. The book guides you through a number of easy to follow examples to learn all the basic properties of Riak. It uses JavaScript as an easy accessible language to understand the examples. It shows that Mathias has done deep research into the database and has put a lot of effort into creating an accessible resource to learn Riak.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
