<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Places on unwiredcouch.com</title>
    <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/places/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Places on unwiredcouch.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language><atom:link href="https://unwiredcouch.com/places/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unwiredcouch.com/places/usa/newyork/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unwiredcouch.com/places/usa/newyork/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve lived in New York City from 2011 - 2017 and absolutely loved it. It&amp;rsquo;s one
of my absolutely favourite cities in the world. This list is a selection of
places I went to that I enjoyed enough to do more than once.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve lived in New York City from 2011 - 2017 and absolutely loved it. It&rsquo;s one
of my absolutely favourite cities in the world. This list is a selection of
places I went to that I enjoyed enough to do more than once.</p>
<h3 id="coffee">Coffee</h3>
<h4 id="sweetleaf"><a href="https://www.sweetleafcoffee.com/">Sweetleaf</a></h4>
<p>A regular spot for coffee and quick snacks. They mostly have sweet stuff and
the location and coffee is great.</p>
<h4 id="brooklyn-roasting-company"><a href="https://brooklynroasting.com/">Brooklyn Roasting Company</a></h4>
<p>They (used to?) have a really nice location in Dumbo near the Etsy office. So
it was basically the default place to get coffee for me for quite a while.</p>
<h3 id="food">Food</h3>
<h4 id="peter-pan"><a href="https://www.peterpandonuts.com/">Peter Pan&rsquo;s Donuts</a></h4>
<p>I used to live on the block of Peter Pan&rsquo;s Donuts and definitely ate way too
many donuts during that time. They have both bagels and donuts in the classic
varieties and definitely recommend going there.</p>
<h4 id="eagle-trading-company"><a href="http://www.eagletradingco.nyc/">Eagle Trading Company</a></h4>
<p>I used to live close by this place and had breakfast there every weekend
basically. They have a variety of really good sandwiches and decent coffee.
And the atmosphere and staff is great.</p>
<h4 id="black-forest-brooklyn"><a href="https://www.blackforestbrooklyn.com/">Black Forest Brooklyn</a></h4>
<p>German food in Brooklyn and it&rsquo;s as legit as it gets. Coming here for food
really felt like coming home. I don&rsquo;t remember if there are many vegan options
but the Schnitzel is great.</p>
<h4 id="smorgasburg"><a href="https://www.smorgasburg.com/">Smorgasburg</a></h4>
<p>The Smorgasburg open air food market in Williamsburg always has a great mix of
different things to try. It&rsquo;s generally pretty crowded but worth it to find a
variety of food things to try.</p>
<h4 id="van-leeuwen-ice-cream"><a href="https://vanleeuwenicecream.com/scoop-shops/#New-York">Van Leeuwen Ice Cream</a></h4>
<p>I went to their Greenpoint location a lot and my favourite was the vegan
peanut butter milkshake. Works well when it&rsquo;s hot outside.</p>
<h4 id="la-bagel-delight-dumbo"><a href="https://www.bageldumbo.com/">La Bagel Delight Dumbo</a></h4>
<p>This was a regular place I went to when I didn&rsquo;t eat breakfast at home. They
are usually pretty busy around breakfast and lunch time and have a huge
variety of bagels, spreads, and toppings.</p>
<h4 id="calexico"><a href="https://www.calexico.com">Calexico</a></h4>
<p>Another regular dinner (or lunch) place was Calexico for me. A burrito is
always a good choice for me and their nachos are also delicious. They also had
a cart in Dumbo occasionally which was perfect to also get lunch during the
workweek there.</p>
<h4 id="bakeri"><a href="https://www.bakeribrooklyn.com/new-page">Bakeri</a></h4>
<p>Bakeri has really good bread and other baked foods like croissants, danishes,
and sweet as well as savory options. And the location in Greenpoint is super
cute.</p>
<h4 id="baker"><a href="https://bakersdozengreenpoint.com/">Baker&rsquo;s Dozen</a></h4>
<p>Baker&rsquo;s Dozen has a large variety of bagels and toppings and the most
energized staff I&rsquo;ve ever seen. I&rsquo;ve definitely gotten bagels there while the
whole crew was singing along to a Good Charlotte song on the radio.</p>
<h4 id="front-street-pizza"><a href="https://www.frontstreetpizzabrooklyn.com/">Front Street Pizza</a></h4>
<p>Another one close to the Etsy office that I&rsquo;ve gotten a ton of lunches in. The
slices are great, but so are the (veggie) burgers.</p>
<h4 id="shake-shack-burgers"><a href="https://shakeshack.com/#/">Shake Shack Burgers</a></h4>
<p>Shake Shack was the burger place I definitely tried to not go to too much.
They were also close to the office which made it really hard. And having a
milkshake and a shack stack was just a really tempting offer for lunch.</p>
<h3 id="parks-and-outdoor-spaces">Parks and Outdoor Spaces</h3>
<h4 id="brooklyn-bridge-park"><a href="https://www.brooklynbridgepark.org/">Brooklyn Bridge Park</a></h4>
<p>I spent a lot of time there walking around on 1:1s, hanging out, and playing
basketball. They had improved it a ton while I was living there and it was
always really nice to have such a great park close to the office.</p>
<h4 id="prospect-park"><a href="https://www.nycgovparks.org/parks/B073/">Prospect Park</a></h4>
<p>Prospect Park is a pretty well known park in Brooklyn and rightfully so. It&rsquo;s
pretty big and really nice to walk with lots of bike riding options.</p>
<h4 id="highline"><a href="https://www.thehighline.org/">Highline</a></h4>
<p>The High Line is a nice park to walk built on a historic, elevated rail line.</p>
<h3 id="misc">Misc</h3>
<h4 id="east-river-ferry"><a href="https://www.ferry.nyc/routes-and-schedules/route/east-river/">East River Ferry</a></h4>
<p>I used to take the ferry to work every day and it was the best commute I ever
had. Especially on sunny days it&rsquo;s such a great view along the Manhattan
skyline and the Brooklyn waterfront.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
